中文字幕
All right.
This is CS50 and this is the start of week two.
中文字幕
And you'll recall that over the past couple of weeks,
we've been building up.
中文字幕
First initially from Scratch, the graphical programming language
that we then, just last week, translated to the equivalent program NC.
中文字幕
And of course, there's a lot more syntax now.
It's entirely text but the ideas, recall, were fundamentally the same.
中文字幕
The catch is that computers don't understand this.
They only understand what language?
中文字幕
zeros and ones or binary.
And so there's a requisite step in order for us to get from this code to binary.
中文字幕
And what was that step or that program or process called?
Yeah, so compiling.
中文字幕
And of course, recall as you've now experimented
with this past week that to compile a program,
中文字幕
you can use clang for C, language.
And you can just say clang and then the name of the file
中文字幕
that you want to compile.
And that outputs by default a pretty oddly named program.
中文字幕
Just a dot out.
Which stands for assembler output.
中文字幕
More on that in just a moment.
But recall too that you can override that default behavior.
中文字幕
And you can actually say, Output instead a program
called, hello instead of just a dot out.
中文字幕
But you can go one step further, and you actually use Make.
And Make it self is not a compiler, it's a build utility.
中文字幕
But in layman's terms, what does it do for us?
compiles it.
中文字幕
And it essentially figures out all of those otherwise cryptic
looking command line arguments.
中文字幕
Like dash-o something, and so forth.
So that the program is built just the way
中文字幕
we want it without our having to remember
those seemingly magical incantations.
中文字幕
And though that only works for programs as simple as this.
In fact, some of you with the most recent problems that
中文字幕
might have encountered compilation errors that we actually
did not encounter deliberately in class because Make was helping us out.
中文字幕
In fact, as soon as you enhance a program
to actually take user input using CS50's library by including CS50 dot H,
中文字幕
some of you might have realized that all of a sudden the sandbox,
and more generally Clang, didn't know what get_string was.
中文字幕
And frankly, Clang might not even known what a string was.
And that's because those two are features of CS50's library
中文字幕
that you have to teach Clang about.
But it's not enough to teach Clang what they look like, as by including CS50.h.
中文字幕
Turns out there's a missing step that Make helps us solve
but that you too can just solve manually if you want.
中文字幕
And by that I mean this, instead of compiling a program with just Clang,
hello.c.
中文字幕
When you want to use CS50's library, you actually
need to add this additional command line argument.
中文字幕
Specifically at the end, can't go in the beginning like dash-O.
And dash-L stands for link.
中文字幕
And this is a way of telling Clang, by the way when compiling my program,
please link in CS50's zeros and ones that we the staff
中文字幕
wrote some weeks ago and installed in the sandbox for you.
So you've got your zeros and ones and then
中文字幕
you've got our zeros and ones so to speak.
And dash-LCS50 says to link them together.
中文字幕
So if you were getting some kind of undefined reference error to get_string
or you didn't--
中文字幕
you weren't able to compile a program that just used any of the get functions
from CS50's library.
中文字幕
Odds are, this simple change dash-LCS50 would have fixed.
But of course, this isn't interesting stuff to remember, let alone
中文字幕
remembering how to use dash-0 as well, at which point
the command gets really tedious to type.
中文字幕
So here comes, Make again.
Make automates all of this for us.
中文字幕
And in fact, if you henceforth start running Make and then
pay closer attention to the fairly long line of output that it outputs,
中文字幕
you'll actually see mention of dash-LCS50,
you'll see mention of even dash-LM, which stands for math.
中文字幕
So if you're using round, for instance, you
might have discovered that round two also
中文字幕
doesn't work out of the box unless you use Make itself
or this more nuanced approach.
中文字幕
So this is all to say that compiling is a bit of a white lie.
Like, yes you've been compiling and you've been going from source code
中文字幕
to machine code.
But it turns out that there's been a number of other steps happening
中文字幕
for you that we're going to just slap some labels on today.
At the end of the day, we're just breaking the abstraction.
中文字幕
So compiling is this abstraction from source code to machine code.
Let's just kind of zoom in briefly to appreciate
中文字幕
what it is that's going on in hopes that it makes the code we're
compiling a little more understandable.
中文字幕
So step one of four, when it comes to actually compiling a program
is called Pre-processing.
中文字幕
So recall that this program we just looked at had a couple of
includes at the top of the file.
中文字幕
These are generally known as pre-processor directives.
Not a particularly interesting term but they're
中文字幕
demarcated by the hash at the start of these lines.
That's a signal to Clang that these things should be handled first.
中文字幕
Preprocessed.
Process before everything else.
中文字幕
And in fact, the reason for this we did discuss last week, inside of CS50.h
is what, for instance?
中文字幕
Specifically, the declaration of get strings.
So there's some lines of code, the prototype if you recall,
中文字幕
that one line of code that teaches Clang what the inputs to get_string are
and what the outputs are.
中文字幕
The return type and the arguments, so to speak.
And so when you have include CS50.h at the top of the file, what
中文字幕
is happening when you first run Clang during this so-called pre-processing
step, is Clang looks on the hard drive for the file literally called CS50.h.
中文字幕
It grabs its contents and essentially finds and replaces this line here.
So somewhere in CS50.h is a line like this yellow one here
中文字幕
that says get_string, is a function that returns a string.
And it takes as input, the so-called argument, a string
中文字幕
that we'll call prompt.
Meanwhile, with include standard I/O. What's the point of including that?
中文字幕
What is declared inside of that file presumably?
Yeah?
中文字幕
It's the standard inputs and outputs.
Standard inputs and outputs.
中文字幕
And more specifically, what example there of?
What function?
中文字幕
So printf.
The other function we keep using.
中文字幕
So inside of standard io.h, somewhere on the sandbox's hard drive
is similarly a line of code that frankly looks a little more cryptic
中文字幕
but we'll come back to this sort of thing
down the road, that says print if is a function.
中文字幕
Happens to return on int, but more on that another time.
Happens to take a char* format.
中文字幕
But more on that another time.
Indeed, this is one of the reasons we hide
中文字幕
this detail early on because there's some syntax that's
just a distraction for now.
中文字幕
But that's all that's going on.
The sharp include sign is just finding and replacing the contents.
中文字幕
Plus dot, dot, dot, a bunch of other things in those files as well.
So when we say pre-processing, we just mean
中文字幕
that that's getting substituted in so you don't have to copy and paste
this sort of thing manually yourself.
中文字幕
So "compiling" is a word that actually has a well-defined meaning.
Once you've preprocessed your code, and your code looks essentially like this,
中文字幕
unbeknownst to you, then comes the actual compilation step.
And this code here gets turned into this code here.
中文字幕
Now this is scary-looking, and this is the sort of thing
that if you take a class like CS61 at Harvard,
中文字幕
or, more generally, systems programming, so to speak,
you might see something like this.
中文字幕
This is x86 64-bit assembly instructions.
And the only thing interesting about that claim for the moment
中文字幕
is that assembly--
I kind of alluded to that earlier-- assembler output, a.out.
中文字幕
There's actually a relationship here, but long story short, these
are the lower level instructions that only the CPU,
中文字幕
the brain inside your computer, actually understands.
Your CPU does not understand C. It doesn't understand Python or C++
中文字幕
or Java or any language with which you might be familiar.
It only understands this cryptic-looking thing.
中文字幕
But frankly, from the looks of it, you might glean that probably not so much
fun to program in this.
中文字幕
I mean, arguably, it's not that much fun to program yet in C,
So this looks even more cryptic.
中文字幕
But that's OK.
C and lots of languages are just these abstractions
中文字幕
on top of the lower level stuff that the CPUs do actually
understand so that we don't have to worry about it as much.
中文字幕
But if we highlight a few terms, here you'll see some familiar things.
So main is mentioned in this so-called assembly code.
中文字幕
You see mention of get string and printf,
so we're not losing information.
中文字幕
It's just being presented in really a different language, assembly language.
Now you can glean, perhaps, from some of the names of these instructions,
中文字幕
this is what Intel Inside means.
When Intel or any brand of CPU understands instructions,
中文字幕
it means things like pushing and moving and subtracting and calling.
These are all low level verbs, functions,
中文字幕
if you will, but at the level of the CPU.
But for more on that, you can take entire courses.
中文字幕
But just to take the hood off of this for today,
this is a step that's been happening for us magically unbeknownst
中文字幕
to us, thanks to Clang.
So assembling-- now that you've got this cryptic-looking code that we will never
中文字幕
see again-- we'll never need to output again--
what do you do with it?
中文字幕
Well, you said earlier that computers only understand zeros and ones,
so the third step is actually to convert this assembly language to actual zeros
中文字幕
and ones that now look like this.
So the assembling step happening, unbeknownst to you,
中文字幕
every time you run Clang or, in turn, run
make, we're getting zeros and ones out of the assembly code,
中文字幕
and we're getting the assembly code out of your C-code.
But here's the fourth and final step.
中文字幕
Recall that we need to link in other people's zeros and ones.
If you're using printf you didn't write that.
中文字幕
Someone else created those zeros and ones, the patterns
that the computer understands.
中文字幕
You didn't create get string.
We did, so you need access to those zeros and ones
中文字幕
so that your program can use them as well.
So linking, essentially, does this.
中文字幕
If you've written a program-- for instance, hello.c--
and it happens to use a couple of other libraries,
中文字幕
files that other people wrote of useful code
for you, like cs50.c, which does exist somewhere,
中文字幕
and even stdio.c, which does exist somewhere,
or technically, Standard IO is such a big library,
中文字幕
they actually put printf in a file specifically called printf.c.
But somewhere in the sandbox's hard drive, in all of our Macs and PCs,
中文字幕
if they support compiling, are, for instance, files like these.
But we've got to convert this to zeros and ones, this, and this,
中文字幕
and then somehow combine them.
So pictorially, this just looks a bit like this.
中文字幕
And this is all happening automatically by Clang.
Hello.c, the code you wrote, gets compiled
中文字幕
to assembly, which then gets assembled into zeros and ones, so-called machine
code or object code.
中文字幕
Cs50.c-- we did this for you before the semester started.
Printf was done way before any of us started decades
中文字幕
ago and looks like this.
These are three separate files, though, so the linking step literally
中文字幕
means, link all of these things together, and combine the zeros
and ones from, like, three, at least, separate files,
中文字幕
and just combine them in such a way that now
the CPU knows how to use not just your code but printf and get string
中文字幕
and so forth.
So last week, we introduced compiling as an abstraction,
中文字幕
if you will, and this is all that we've really meant this whole time.
But now that we've seen what's going on underneath the hood,
中文字幕
and we can stipulate that my CPU that looks physically
like this, albeit smaller in a laptop or desktop,
中文字幕
knows how to deal with all of that.
So any questions on these four steps--
中文字幕
pre-processing, compiling, assembling, linking?
But generally, now, we can just call them compiling, as most people do.
中文字幕
Any questions?
Yeah.
中文字幕
How does the CPU know that  is there?
Is that ?
中文字幕
Not in the pre-processing step,
so the question is, how does the computer
中文字幕
know that printf is the only function that's there?
Essentially, when you're linking in code,
中文字幕
only the requisite zeros and ones are typically linked in.
Sometimes you get more than you actually need, if it's a big library,
中文字幕
but that's OK, too.
Those zeros and ones are just never used by the CPU.
中文字幕
Good question.
Other questions?
中文字幕
OK, all right.
So now that we know this is possible, let's start
中文字幕
to build our way back up, because everyone here
probably knows now that when writing in C, which
中文字幕
is kind of up here conceptually, like, it
is not without its hurdles and problems and bugs and mistakes.
中文字幕
So let's introduce a few techniques and tools with which you can henceforth,
starting this week and beyond, trying to troubleshoot those problems yourself
中文字幕
rather than just trying to read through the cryptic-looking error messages
or reach out for help to another human.
中文字幕
Let's see if software can actually answer some of these questions for you.
So let me go ahead and do this.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and open up a sandbox here,
and I'm going to go ahead and create a new file called
中文字幕
buggy0.c in which I will, this time, deliberately introduce a bug.
I'm going to go ahead and create my function called
中文字幕
main, which, again, is the default, like when green flag is clicked.
And I'm going to go ahead and say, printf, quote, unquote,
中文字幕
"Hello world/m."
All right.
中文字幕
Looks pretty good.
I'm going to go ahead and compile buggy0, Enter,
中文字幕
and of course, I get a bunch of error messages here.
Let me zoom in on them.
中文字幕
Fortunately, I only have two, but remember, you have to, have to,
have to always scroll up to look at the first,
中文字幕
because there might just be an annoying cascading effect from one earlier
bug to the later.
中文字幕
So buggy0.c, line 5, is what this means, character 5, so like 5 spaces in,
implicitly declaring library function printf with dot, dot, dot.
中文字幕
So you're going to start to see this pretty often if you make
this particular mistake or oversight.
中文字幕
Implicitly declaring something means you forgot
to teach Clang that something exists.
中文字幕
And you probably know from experience, perhaps now, what the solution is.
What's the first mistake I made here?
中文字幕
Yeah, I didn't include the header file,
so to speak, for the library.
中文字幕
I'm missing, at the top of the file, include stdio.h,
in which printf is defined.
中文字幕
But let's propose that you're not quite sure how to get to that point,
and how can we get, actually, some help with this?
中文字幕
Let me actually increase the size of my terminal
here, and recall that just a moment ago, I ran makebuggy0,
中文字幕
which yielded the errors that I saw.
It turns out that installed in the sandbox
中文字幕
is a command that we, the staff, wrote called help50.
And this is just a program we wrote that takes as input any error
中文字幕
messages that your code or some program has outputted.
We kind of look for familiar words and phrases,
中文字幕
just like a TF would in office hours, and if we recognize some error message,
we're going to try to provide, either rhetorically or explicitly,
中文字幕
some advice on how to handle.
So if I go ahead and run this command now, notice there's a bit more output.
中文字幕
I see exactly the same output in white and green and red as before,
but down below is some yellow, which comes specifically from help50.
中文字幕
And if I go ahead and zoom in on this, you'll
see that the line of output that we recognized
中文字幕
is this one, that same one I verbally drew attention
to before-- buggy0.c, line 5, error, implicitly declaring library function
中文字幕
printf, and so forth.
So here, without the background highlighting, but still in yellow,
中文字幕
is our advice or a question a TF or CA might ask you in office hours.
Well, did you forget to include stdio.h in which printf
中文字幕
is declared atop your file?
And hopefully, our questions, rhetorical or otherwise, are correct,
中文字幕
and that will get you further along.
So let's go ahead and try that advice.
中文字幕
So include stdio.h.
Now let me go ahead and go back down here.
中文字幕
And if you don't like clutter, you can type "clear,"
or hit Control+L in the terminal window to keep cleaning it like I do.
中文字幕
If you want to go ahead now and run makebuggy0, Enter, fewer errors,
so that's progress, and not the same.
中文字幕
So this one's, perhaps, a little easier.
Reading the line, what line of code is buggy here?
中文字幕
Forgot the semicolon.
Yeah, so this is now still on line 5, it turns out,
中文字幕
but for a different reason.
I seem to be missing a semi-colon.
中文字幕
But I could similarly ask help50 for help with that
and hope that it recognizes my error.
中文字幕
So this, too, should start being your first instinct.
If on first glance, you don't really understand
中文字幕
what an error message is doing, even though you've
scrolled to the very first one, like literally ask this program for help
中文字幕
by rerunning the exact same command you just
ran, but prefix it with help50 and a space,
中文字幕
and that will run help50 for you.
Any questions on that process?
中文字幕
All right, let's take a look at one other program,
for instance, that, this time, has a different error involved in it.
中文字幕
So how about-- let me go ahead and whip up a quick program here.
I'll call this buggy2.c for consistency with some of the samples
中文字幕
we have online for you later.
And in this example, I'm going to go ahead and write the correct thing
中文字幕
at first, stdio.h, and then I'm going to have int main void, which
just gets my whole program started.
中文字幕
And then I'm going to have a loop, and recall for--
[CLEARS THROAT] excuse me-- Mario or some other program,
中文字幕
you might have done something like int i get 0, i is less than or equal to--
let's do this 10 times, and then i++.
中文字幕
And all I want to do in this program is print out that value of i, as I can do,
with the %i placeholder-- so a simple program.
中文字幕
Just want it to count from 0 to 10.
So let's go ahead and run buggy2, or rather, I want to--
中文字幕
let's not print up--
rewind.
中文字幕
Let's go ahead and just print out a hash symbol
and not spoil the solution this way.
中文字幕
So here, I go ahead and print out buggy2.
My goal is now I will stipulate to print out just 10 hash symbols, one per line,
中文字幕
which is what I want to do here.
And now I'm going to go ahead and run ./buggy2, and I should see, hopefully,
中文字幕
10 hashes.
And I kind of spoiled this a little bit, but what do I instead see?
中文字幕
Yeah, I think I see more than I expect.
And we can kind of zoom in here and double check, so 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7,
中文字幕
8, 9, 10, ooh, 11.
11.
中文字幕
Now some of your eyes might already be darting to what the solution should be,
but let's just propose that it's not obvious.
中文字幕
And if it is actually not obvious, all the better, so how might
you go about diagnosing this kind of problem, short of just
中文字幕
reaching out and asking a human for help.
This is not a problem that help50 can help with,
中文字幕
because it's not an error message.
Your program is working.
中文字幕
It's just not outputting what you wanted it to work,
but it's not an error message from the compiler with which help50 can help.
中文字幕
So you want to kind of get eyes into what your program is doing,
and you want to understand, why are you printing 11 when you really
中文字幕
are setting this up from 0 to 10?
Well, one of the most common techniques in C or any language,
中文字幕
honestly, is to use printf for just other purposes-- diagnostic purposes.
For instance, there's not much going on in this program,
中文字幕
but I'd argue that it would be interesting for me to know,
and therefore understand my program, by just,
中文字幕
let's print out this value of i on each iteration,
as by doing the line of code that I earlier did,
中文字幕
and just say something literally like, i is %i.
I'm going to remove this ultimately, because it's
中文字幕
going to make my program look a little silly,
but it's going to help me understand what's going on.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and recompile buggy2, ./bugg2, and this time,
I see a lot more output.
中文字幕
But if I zoom in, now it's kind of--
now the computer is essentially helping me understand what's going on.
中文字幕
When i is 0, here's one of them.
When i is 1, here's another.
中文字幕
I is 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, and that looks good.
But if we scroll a little further, it feels a little problematic
中文字幕
that i can also be 10.
So what's logically the bug in this program?
中文字幕
Yeah.
I use less than or equal to, because I kind of confuse the paradigm.
中文字幕
Like programmers tend to start counting at zero,
apparently, but I want to do this 10 times, and in the human world,
中文字幕
if I want to do something 10 times, I might count up to and including 10.
But you can't have it both ways.
中文字幕
You can't start at zero and end at 10 if you
want to do something exactly 10 times.
中文字幕
So there's a couple of possibilities here.
How might we fix this?
中文字幕
Yeah, so we could certainly change it to less than.
What's another correct approach?
中文字幕
Yeah, so we could leave this alone and just start counting at one,
and if you're not actually printing the values in your actual program,
中文字幕
that might be perfectly reasonable, too.
It's just not conventional.
中文字幕
Get comfortable with, quickly, just counting from zero, because that's just
what most everyone does these days.
中文字幕
But the technique here is just use printf.
Like, when in doubt, literally use printf on this line, on this line,
中文字幕
on this line.
Anywhere something is interesting maybe going on in your program,
中文字幕
just use it to print out the strings that are in your variables,
print out the integers that are in your variables, or anything else.
中文字幕
And it allows you to kind of see, so to speak,
what's going on inside of your program, printf.
中文字幕
One last tool-- so it's not uncommon, when writing code,
to maybe get a little sloppy early on, especially when you're not
中文字幕
quite familiar with the patterns.
And for instance, if I go ahead and do this
中文字幕
by deleting a whole bunch of whitespace, even after fixing this mistake
by going from zero to 10, is this program now correct,
中文字幕
if the goal is to print 10 hashes?
Yeah, I heard yes.
中文字幕
Why is it correct?
In what sense?
中文字幕
Yeah, exactly.
It still works.
中文字幕
It prints out the 10 hashes, one per line,
but it's poorly written in the sense of style.
中文字幕
So recall that we tend to evaluate, and the world
tends to think about code in at least three ways.
中文字幕
One, the correctness-- does it do what it's supposed to do,
like print 10 hashes?
中文字幕
And yes, it does, because all I did was delete whitespace.
I didn't actually change or break the code after making that fix.
中文字幕
Two is design, like how thoughtful, how well-written is the code?
And frankly, it's kind of hard to write this in too many ways,
中文字幕
because it's so few lines.
But you'll see over time, as your programs grow,
中文字幕
the teaching fellows and staff can provide you with feedback
on the design of your code.
中文字幕
But style is relatively easy.
And I've been teaching it mostly by way of example, if you will,
中文字幕
because I've been very methodically indenting my code
and making sure everything looks very pretty, or at least pretty
中文字幕
to a trained eye.
But this, let's just stipulate, is not pretty.
中文字幕
Like, left aligning everything still works, not incorrect,
but it's poorly styled.
中文字幕
And what would be an argument for not writing code
like this and, instead, writing code the way
中文字幕
I did a moment ago, albeit after fixing the bug?
Yeah.
中文字幕
It'll help you identify each little subroutine that
goes through the thing, so you know this section is here.
中文字幕
Yeah.
next one, so you know where everything is.
中文字幕
Exactly.
Let me summarize this.
中文字幕
It allows you to see, more visually, what
are the individual subroutines or blocks of code doing
中文字幕
that are associated with each other?
Scratch is colorful, and it has shapes, like the hugging shape
中文字幕
that a lot of the control blocks make, to make
clear visually to the programmer that this block encompasses others,
中文字幕
and, therefore, this repeats block or this forever block
is doing these things again and again and again.
中文字幕
That's the role that these curly braces serve, and indentation
in this and in other contexts just helps it
中文字幕
become more obvious to the programmer what is inside of what
and what is happening where.
中文字幕
So this is just better written, because you
can see that the code inside of main is everything that's indented here.
中文字幕
The code that's inside the for loop is everything that's indented here.
So it's just for us human readers, teaching fellows
中文字幕
in the case of a course, or colleagues in the case of the real world.
But suppose that you don't quite see these patterns too readily initially.
中文字幕
That, too, is fine.
CS50 has on its website what we call a style guide.
中文字幕
It's just a summary of what your code should
look like when using certain features of C-- loops,
中文字幕
conditions, variables, functions, and so forth.
And it's linked on the course's website.
中文字幕
But there's also a tool that you can use when
writing your code that'll help you clean it up and make it consistent,
中文字幕
not just for the sake of making it consistent with the style guide,
but just making your own code more readable.
中文字幕
So for instance, if I go ahead and run a command called
style50 on this program, buggy2.c, and then hit Enter,
中文字幕
I'm going to see some output that's colorful.
I see my own code in white, and then I see, anywhere
中文字幕
I should have indented, green spaces that
are sort of encouraging me to put space, space, space, space here.
中文字幕
Put space, space, space, space here.
Put eight spaces here, four spaces here, and so forth,
中文字幕
and then it's reminding me I should add comments as well.
This is a short program-- doesn't necessarily
中文字幕
need a lot of commenting to explain what's going on.
But just one //, like we saw last week to explain,
中文字幕
maybe at the top of the file or top the block of the code,
would make style50 happy as well.
中文字幕
So let's do that.
Let me go ahead and take its advice and actually indent this with Tab,
中文字幕
this with Tab, this with Tab, this with Tab, and this once more.
And you'll notice that on your keyboard, even though you're hitting Tab,
中文字幕
it's actually converting it for you, which is very common to four spaces,
so you don't have to hit the spacebar four times.
中文字幕
Just get into the habit of using Tab.
And let me go ahead and write a comment here.
中文字幕
"Print 10 hashes."
This way, my colleagues, my teaching fellow, myself in a week
中文字幕
don't have to read my own code again and figure out what it's doing.
I can read the comments alone per the //.
中文字幕
If I run style50 again, now it looks good.
It's in accordance with the style guide, and it's just more prettily written,
中文字幕
so pretty printed would be a term of art in programming
when your code looks good and isn't just correct.
中文字幕
Any questions then?
Yeah.
中文字幕
I tried using  this past week
and it said I needed a new program.
中文字幕
That's--
it wasn't enabled for the first week of the class.
中文字幕
It's enabled as of right now and henceforth.
Other questions?
中文字幕
No.
All right, so just to recap then, three tools to have in the proverbial toolbox
中文字幕
now are help50 anytime you see an error message that you don't understand,
whether it's with make or Clang or, perhaps, something else.
中文字幕
Printf-- when you've got a logical program--
a bug in your program, and it's just not working the way it's supposed to
中文字幕
or the way the problem set tells you it should, and then style50
when you want to make sure that, does my code look right in terms of style,
中文字幕
and is it as readable as possible?
And honestly, you'll find us at office hours and the like
中文字幕
often encouraging you, hey, before we answer this question,
can you please run style50 on your code?
中文字幕
Can you please clean up your code, because it just makes our lives, too,
as other humans so much easier when we can understand what's
中文字幕
going on without having to visually figure out what parentheses and curly
braces line up.
中文字幕
And so do get into that habit, because it
will save you time from having to waste time parsing things visually yourself.
中文字幕
All right.
So there's not just CPUs in computers.
中文字幕
CPUs are the brains, central processing unit,
and that's why we keep emphasizing the instructions that computers understand.
中文字幕
There's also this, which we saw last time, too.
This is an example of what type of hardware?
中文字幕
RAM.
RAM, or Random Access Memory.
中文字幕
This is the type of memory that laptops, desktops, servers
have that is used whenever you run a program or open a file.
中文字幕
There's another type of memory called hard drives or solid state drives,
which you're probably familiar as a consumer,
中文字幕
and that's just where your files are stored permanently.
Your battery can die.
中文字幕
You can pull the plug from your laptop or desktop,
and any files saved on a hard drive are persistent.
中文字幕
They stay there because of the technology
being used to implement that.
中文字幕
But RAM is more ephemeral.
RAM is powered only by electricity.
中文字幕
It's only used when the power is on or the battery is charged,
and it's where your files and programs live effectively when
中文字幕
you double click on them and open them.
So when you double click on something like Microsoft Word,
中文字幕
it is copied from your hard drive long term into this type of memory,
because this type of memory, though smaller in capacity--
中文字幕
you don't have as many bytes of it--
but it is much, much, much, much faster.
中文字幕
Similarly, when you open a document, or you go to a web page,
the contents of the file you're seeing are stored in this type of hardware,
中文字幕
because even though you don't have terribly many bytes of it,
it's just much, much, much, much faster.
中文字幕
And so this will be thematic in computer science and in hardware.
You sort of have lots of cheap, slow stuff,
中文字幕
like hard disk space, relatively speaking, and you have a little less
of the more expensive but faster stuff like RAM.
中文字幕
And you have just one, usually, CPU, which is the really fast thing that
can do a billion things per second.
中文字幕
But it, too, is more expensive.
So there's four visible chips on this thing, if you will.
中文字幕
And we won't get into the details of how these things work, but let's
just zoom in on this one black chip here and focus on it
中文字幕
as being representative as some amount of memory.
Maybe it's one megabyte, one million bytes.
中文字幕
Maybe it's even one gigabyte these days, one billion bytes.
But this is to say that this chip can be thought of as just having
中文字幕
a bunch of bytes in it.
This is not to scale.
中文字幕
You have many more bytes than these, but let
me propose that you just think of each of these squares
中文字幕
here as representing one byte.
So the very first byte of memory I have access to is here.
中文字幕
Next one is here, and so forth.
And the fact that they wrap around is just an artist rendition.
中文字幕
These things you can think of just virtually as going
left to right, not in any kind of grid, but physically, they look like this.
中文字幕
So when you actually create a variable in a program like C,
like you need a char.
中文字幕
A char tends to be one byte or eight bits,
and so that means when you have a variable of type char in a C program,
中文字幕
it goes, literally, physically in one of these boxes,
inside of your computer's RAM.
中文字幕
So for instance, it might take up this much space at top left.
If you have a bigger type of data, so you
中文字幕
have an integer, which tends to be four bytes or 32 bits,
you might need more than one square, so the computer might give you access
中文字幕
to four squares instead.
And you have 32 bits spanning that region of memory.
中文字幕
But honestly, I chose those boxes arbitrarily.
They could be anywhere in that chip or in any of the other chips.
中文字幕
It's up to the computer to just remember where they are for you.
You don't need to remember that, per se.
中文字幕
But if we think about this grid, it turns out
this is actually very valuable that we have chunks of memory--
中文字幕
bytes, if you will--
that are back to back to back to back.
中文字幕
And in fact, there's a word for this technique.
This is contiguous memory--
中文字幕
back to back to back to back to back.
And in general, in programming, this is referred to as an array.
中文字幕
You might recall from Scratch, if you use this feature,
it actually has things called lists, which
中文字幕
are exactly that-- lists of values, lists of words, lists of strings.
An array is just a contiguous chunk of memory, such
中文字幕
that you can store something here, something here, something here,
something here, and so forth.
中文字幕
So it turns out an array, this super simple primitive,
is actually incredibly powerful.
中文字幕
Just being able to store things in my computer's memory
back to back to back to back enables so many possibilities, both design-wise,
中文字幕
like how well I can write my code, and also how fast I can make my code run.
So let me go ahead and take out an example.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and open up, for instance, a new file in a sandbox,
and we'll call this score0.
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and close this one, create a new file called scores0.c.
And in this file, let's go ahead and write a relatively simple program.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and, as usual, give myself access
to some helpful functions-- cs50.h and stdio.h.
中文字幕
And no need to copy all this down verbatim, if you don't like.
Everything will have or is already on the course's website.
中文字幕
Let me start my program as usual with int main void.
And then let me write a program, as this program's name implies,
中文字幕
that, like, asks the user for three scores on recent problem sets,
quizzes, whatever, and then kind of creates a very simple chart of them,
中文字幕
like a bar chart to kind of help me visualize how well
or how poorly I did on something.
中文字幕
So if I want to get an integer, no surprise,
we can use the get int function, and I can just
中文字幕
ask the user for their first score.
But I should probably do something with this score,
中文字幕
and on the left hand side of this, what do I typically put?
Yeah.
中文字幕
So int-- sure, score 1 equals this, and then my semi-colon.
So you might not have had many occasions to use ints just yet,
中文字幕
but get int is in the cs50 library.
This is the so-called prompt that the human
中文字幕
sees, and let me actually fix my space, because I
want the human to see the space after the colon.
中文字幕
But that's just an aesthetic detail.
And then when I get back this value, its return value--
中文字幕
just like Aaron, last week, handed me a piece of paper,
so does get int hand me a virtual piece of paper with a number
中文字幕
that I'm going to store in a variable called Score 1.
And now just to be clear, what has just happened effectively is this.
中文字幕
The moment you create a variable of type int, which is four bytes,
literally, this is what Clang or, more generally,
中文字幕
the computer has done for you.
That int that the human typed in is stored literally
中文字幕
in four contiguous bytes back to back to back, maybe here, maybe here,
but together.
中文字幕
So that's all that's going on when you're actually using C.
So let me go back into my code here, and now I
中文字幕
want to-- it's not interesting to plot one score.
So let's go ahead and do another.
中文字幕
So int Score 2, get int, get int, and I'll ask the user for score 2,
semi-colon, and then let's get one more, Score 3, get int, call it Score 3,
中文字幕
semi-colon.
All right, so now let me go ahead and generate a bar,
中文字幕
like a bar chart of this.
I'm going to use what we'll call ASCII art.
中文字幕
ASCII, of course, is just text, recall--
very simple text in a computer.
中文字幕
And I can kind of make a bar chart pretty simply by just printing out
like a bunch of hashes horizontally, so a short bar
中文字幕
will represent a small number, and a long bar will represent a big number.
So let me go ahead and say to the user, all right, here's your Score 1.
中文字幕
I'm going to go ahead, then, and say, for int i get 0.
I is less than Score 1, i++.
中文字幕
And now if I scroll down and give myself a bit of room here,
let me go ahead and implement just a simple print.
中文字幕
So go ahead and print out a hash, and then when you're all done with that,
print out a new line at the end of that loop.
中文字幕
And let's just pause there.
Just to recap, I've asked the human for three scores.
中文字幕
I'm only doing something with one of them at the moment, so in fact,
just as a quick check, let me delete those so as to not get ahead of myself.
中文字幕
Let me do make score 0.
Cross my fingers.
中文字幕
OK, no errors.
Now let me go ahead and do ./score0, and your first score on a pset this year
中文字幕
out of 100 has been?
OK, 100.
中文字幕
And good job.
So it's a really long bar, and if we count those up,
中文字幕
hopefully, there's actually 100 bars.
And if we run it again and say, eh, it didn't go so well.
中文字幕
I got a 50.
That's half as big a bar.
中文字幕
So it seems like we're on our way correctness-wise.
So now let me go ahead and get the other scores.
中文字幕
Well, I had them here a moment ago.
So let me go ahead and just, well, copy, paste, and change this to two,
中文字幕
change this to three, change this to three, this to three.
All right, I know how to print bars clearly, so let me go ahead
中文字幕
and do this, and then do this, and then fix the indentation.
I don't want to say Score 1 everywhere.
中文字幕
I want to say a Score 2, Score 2.
I mean you're probably being rubbed the wrong way that this
中文字幕
is both tedious and sloppy, and why?
What am I doing poorly now design-wise?
中文字幕
Copying and pasting code.
Like copy-pasting almost always bad, right?
中文字幕
There's redundancy here, but that's fine.
Let's prioritize correctness, at least, for now.
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and make Score 0.
All right, no mistakes-- ./score0.
中文字幕
And then Tab it.
Let me go ahead now and run--
中文字幕
OK, we got 100 the first time.
We got 50 the--
中文字幕
oh, that's a bug.
What did I do there?
中文字幕
See, this is what happens when you copy-paste.
So let's fix this.
中文字幕
That should say Score 2, so Control+C will quit a program.
Make score 0 will recreate it. ./0, Enter--
中文字幕
all right, here we go.
100, 50.
中文字幕
Let's split the difference--
75.
中文字幕
All right, so this is a simple bar chart horizontally drawn
of each of my three scores, where this is 100, this is 50, and this is 75.
中文字幕
But there's opportunities for improvement here.
So one, it rubbed some folks the wrong way
中文字幕
already that we were literally copying and pasting code.
So where is one opportunity for improvement here?
中文字幕
What should I do instead of copying and pasting that code again and again?
What ingredient can you bring?
中文字幕
OK, so we can use a loop and actually just do the same thing three times.
So let's try that.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and do this.
So let's go ahead and delete the copy-paste I did,
中文字幕
and let me go ahead and say, OK, well, for int i get zero, i less than 3, i++.
Let me create a bracket.
中文字幕
I can highlight multiple lines and hit Tab,
and they'll all indent for me, which is convenient.
中文字幕
And can I do this now, for instance?
Say it a little louder.
中文字幕
If you  to a specific ..
Yeah, I'm a little worried.
中文字幕
As you're noting here, we're using on line 13 here the same variable, so mm.
So it's good instincts, but I feel like the fact
中文字幕
that this program, unlike last week, we're
now collecting multiple pieces of data.
中文字幕
Loops are breaking down for us.
Yeah.
中文字幕
function  takes in--
like you can have it .
中文字幕
OK.
So like an input of how many scores you wanted to enter.
中文字幕
OK.
And then .
中文字幕
Yeah, we can implement another
function that factors out some of this functionality.
中文字幕
Any other thoughts?
Store your scores in an array.
中文字幕
OK, so we could also store our scores in an array.
So let's do these in order then, in fact.
中文字幕
So loops are wonderful when you want to do something again and again
and again, but the whole purpose of a function,
中文字幕
fundamentally, is to factor out common functionality.
And there might still be a loop in the solution,
中文字幕
but the real fundamental problem with what I was doing a moment ago
was I was copying and pasting functionality--
中文字幕
shouldn't need to do that, because in both C and Scratch,
we had the ability to make our own functions.
中文字幕
So let's do that.
Let me undo my loop changes here, just to get us
中文字幕
back to where we were a moment ago.
And let me go ahead and, instead, clean this up a little bit.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and create a new function
down here that I'm going to call, say, Chart, just
中文字幕
to create a chart for myself.
And it's going to take as input a score, but I could call this anything I want.
中文字幕
It's void as its return type, because I don't need it to hand me something
back.
中文字幕
Like I'm not getting a string from the user.
I'm just printing a char.
中文字幕
It's a so-called side effect or output.
Now I'm going to go ahead and do my loop here for int i get 0.
中文字幕
I is less than--
how many hashes do I want to print if I'm being passed in the user score?
中文字幕
Like, is this 3 here?
The score.
中文字幕
The score, so if I'm being
handed a number that's 0 to 100, that's what I want to iterate over.
中文字幕
If my goal here, ultimately--
let me finish this thought-- i++ is [? 2 ?] inside this loop print out one
中文字幕
hash per point in 1's total score.
And just to keep things clean, I'm going to go ahead and put
中文字幕
a new line at the very end of this.
But I think now, I factored out a good amount of the redundancy.
中文字幕
It's not everything, but I've at least now
given myself a function called Chart.
中文字幕
So up here, it looks like I can kind of remove this loop, which
is what I factored out.
中文字幕
That's almost identical, except the variable name was hardcoded.
And I think I could now do chart like this,
中文字幕
and then I maybe could do a little copy-paste, if that's OK, like if maybe
I can get away with just doing this, and then say 2, and then say 3,
中文字幕
and then say 3, and then say 2.
So it's still copy-paste, but it's less.
中文字幕
And it looks better.
It literally fits on the screen, so it's progress-- not perfect, but progress.
中文字幕
Better design, but not perfect.
So is this going to compile?
中文字幕
I'm going to have errors why?
Essentially, it's  the program ..
中文字幕
OK.
Yeah.
中文字幕
We need to declare a ..
OK, good.
中文字幕
So let me induce the actual error, just so we know what problem we're solving.
Let me go ahead and sort of innocently go ahead
中文字幕
and compile Score 0 hoping all is well, but of course,
it's not because of a familiar error up here.
中文字幕
So notice, implicit declaration of function chart is invalid in C99.
So again, implicit declaration of function
中文字幕
just tends to mean Clang does not know what you're talking about.
And you could run help50, and it would probably
中文字幕
provide you with similar advice.
But the gist of this is that chart is not a C function.
中文字幕
It doesn't come with C. I wrote it.
I just wrote it a little too late.
中文字幕
So one solution that we didn't used last week
would be, OK, well, if you don't know what chart is, let me just
中文字幕
go put it where you'll know about it.
And now run make score 0.
中文字幕
OK, problem solved.
So that fixes it, but we fixed it in a different way last week.
中文字幕
And why might we want to stick with last week's approach
and not just copy-paste my function and put it
中文字幕
at the top instead of the bottom?
Yeah, I mean it's kind of a minor concern at the moment,
中文字幕
because this is a pretty short program.
But I'm pushing the main part of my program, literally called Main,
中文字幕
farther and farther down.
And the whole point of reading code is to understand what it's doing.
中文字幕
So if I open this file, and I have to scroll, scroll, scroll, scroll, scroll,
just looking for the main function, it's just bad style.
中文字幕
It's just kind of nice, and it's a good human convention.
Put the main code, the main function, when green flag clicks equivalent,
中文字幕
at the very top.
So C does offer us a solution here.
中文字幕
You just have to provide it with a little hint.
Let me go ahead and cut this from here, put it back down at the bottom here,
中文字幕
and then go ahead and copy-paste only or retype only the value--
whoops-- the value of that first line, which is its so-called prototype.
中文字幕
Give Clang enough information so that it knows what arguments the function
takes, what its return type is, and what its name is, semi-colon,
中文字幕
and that's the so-called declaration or--
and then implement it with the curly braces and all the logic down below.
中文字幕
So let's go ahead and run this.
And if I scroll up here, we'll see-- whoops.
中文字幕
We'll see make score 0.
All right, now we're on our way, score 0.
中文字幕
Enter.
Score 1 is 100, 50, 75, and now we seem to have some good functionality.
中文字幕
But there's still an opportunity, I dare say, for improvement.
And I think the fundamental problem is that I'm still
中文字幕
copy-pasting the little stuff, but I think
the fundamental problem is that I don't have the expressiveness to store
中文字幕
multiple values, unless I, in advance, as the programmer,
give them all unique names, because if I use the same variable for everything,
中文字幕
I couldn't collect all three variables at the top,
and then iterate over all three at the bottom, if I only have one variable.
中文字幕
So I do need three variables, but this doesn't scale very well.
And who knows?
中文字幕
If I want to take in five scores, 10 scores, or more scores,
then I'm really copying and pasting excessively.
中文字幕
So it turns out, indeed, the answer is an array.
So an array, at the end of the day, is just
中文字幕
a side effect of storing stuff in memory back to back to back to back.
But what's powerful about this reality of memory is the following.
中文字幕
I can go ahead here and in, say, a new and more improved
version of this program, do this.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and open this one, which I wrote in advance, called scores2.c.
And in scores2.c, notice we have the following code.
中文字幕
In my main function, I've got a new feature and a new bit of syntax.
This line here that I've highlighted says, hey, Clang,
中文字幕
give me a variable called Scores of type integer,
but please give me three of them.
中文字幕
So the new syntax are your square brackets,
and inside of which is the number of variables you want of that type.
中文字幕
And you don't have to give them unique names.
You literally call them collectively, Scores,
中文字幕
and in English, I deliberately chose a plural to connote as much.
This is an array of values, not a single value.
中文字幕
What can I do next?
Well, here's my for loop for int i get zero i is less than 3 i++,
中文字幕
and now I've solved that earlier problem that was proposed.
Well, just put it in a loop.
中文字幕
Now I can, because now my variables are not called Score 1, Score 2, Score 3,
which I literally had to hard code.
中文字幕
They're just called Scores, and now that they're called Scores,
and I have this square bracket notation, notice what I can do.
中文字幕
I can get an int, and I can say, give me score%i, and plug in i plus 1.
I didn't want to say "zero," because humans
中文字幕
don't count from zero in general.
So this is counting from one, two, and three, but the computer is doing this.
中文字幕
So Scores is a variable.
Bracket, i, close bracket says store the i-th value there.
中文字幕
So i-th is just non-English.
That means go to bracket 0, bracket 1, bracket 2.
中文字幕
So what this effectively means is on the first iteration of the loop, when
i equals 0, this looks like this, effectively.
中文字幕
When i then becomes 1 on the next iteration, then you're doing this.
When i becomes 2 on the final iteration, it looks like this.
中文字幕
When i becomes 3, well, 3 is not less than 3,
and so it doesn't execute again.
中文字幕
So by using i inside of these square brackets, am I indexing into an array?
To index into an array means go to a specific location,
中文字幕
the so-called i-th location, but you start counting at zero.
Just to make this more real, then, if you go back
中文字幕
to this picture of your computer's memory,
this might, therefore, be bracket i, bracket 1--
中文字幕
bracket 0, bracket 1, bracket 2, bracket 3, bracket 4, bracket 50, or wherever.
You can now, using square brackets, get at any of these blocks of memory
中文字幕
to store values for you.
Any questions on what we've just done?
中文字幕
All right, then on the flip side, we can do the exact same thing.
Now when I print my scores, I can similarly iterate from 0 to 3,
中文字幕
and then print out the scores by passing to chart
the same value, the i-th score.
中文字幕
Again, the only new syntax here is variable name, square bracket,
and then a number, like 0, 1, 2, or a variable like i,
中文字幕
and then my chart function down here is exactly the same.
It has no idea an array is even involved, because I'm just
中文字幕
passing in one score at a time.
Now it turns out there's still one bad design decision in this program.
中文字幕
There's still some redundancy, something that I keep typing again
and again and again.
中文字幕
Do any values jump out at you as repeated?
The for loop.
中文字幕
OK, so I've got the for loop in multiple places.
Sure.
中文字幕
And what other value seems to be in multiple places?
It's subtle.
中文字幕
Total number.
Yeah, 3.
中文字幕
Three is in a few places.
It's up here.
中文字幕
It's when I declare the array and ask myself for three scores.
It's here when I'm iterating.
中文字幕
It's not here, because this is a different iteration.
That's just for the hashes.
中文字幕
So in, ironically, three places, have I written 3.
So what does this mean?
中文字幕
Well, suppose next year you take more tests or whatever,
and you need more scores.
中文字幕
You open up your program, and all right, now I've got five scores and five--
whoops, typo already-- five, like this kind of pattern
中文字幕
where you're typing the same thing again and again.
And now the onus is on me, the programmer,
中文字幕
to remember to change the same [? damn ?] value in multiple places--
bad, bad, bad design.
中文字幕
You're going to miss one of those values.
Your program's going to get more complex.
中文字幕
You're going to leave one at 3 and change the other to 5,
and logical errors are eventually going to happen.
中文字幕
So how do we solve this?
The function's not the solution here, because it's not functionality.
中文字幕
It's just a value.
Well, we could use a variable, but a certain type of variable.
中文字幕
These numbers here-- 5, 5, 5 or 3, 3, 3--
are what humans generally refer to as magic numbers.
中文字幕
Like they're numbers, but they're kind of magical,
because you just arbitrarily hardcoded them in random places.
中文字幕
But a better convention would be, often as a global variable, to do this--
int, let's call it "count," equals 3.
中文字幕
So declare a variable of type int that is the number of things
you want, and then type that variable name all throughout your code
中文字幕
so that later on, if you ever want to change this program,
you change it-- whoops-- in one place, and you're
中文字幕
done after recompiling the program.
And actually, I should do a little better than this.
中文字幕
It turns out that if you know you have a variable that you're never going
to change, because it's not supposed to change--
中文字幕
it's supposed to be a constant value--
C also has a special keyword called const, where before the data type,
中文字幕
you say, const int, and then the name and then the value, and this way,
the compiler, Clang, will make sure that you, the human,
中文字幕
don't screw up and accidentally try to change the count anywhere else.
There's one other thing notable.
中文字幕
I also capitalize this whole thing for some reason--
human convention.
中文字幕
Anytime you capitalize all of the letters in a variable name,
the convention is that that means it's global.
中文字幕
That means it's defined way up top, and you can use it anywhere, therefore,
because it's outside all curly braces.
中文字幕
But it's meant to imply and remind you that this is special.
It's not just a so-called local variable inside
中文字幕
of a function or inside of a loop or the like.
Any questions on that?
中文字幕
Yeah.
What is ?
中文字幕
Why do you have i plus 1?
Oh, why do I have i plus 1?
中文字幕
Let me run this program real quick.
Why do I have i plus 1 in this line here, is the question.
中文字幕
So let me go ahead and run make scores 2--
whoops-- in my directory.
中文字幕
Make scores 2 ./scores2, Enter.
I wanted just the human to see Score 1 and Score 2 and Score 3.
中文字幕
I didn't want him or her to see Score 0, Score 1, Score 2, because it just looks
lame to the human.
中文字幕
The computer needs to think in terms of zeros.
My humans and my users do not, so just an aesthetic.
中文字幕
Other questions.
Yeah.
中文字幕
Ah, really good question.
And I actually thought about this last night
中文字幕
when trying to craft this example.
Why don't I just combine these two for loops,
中文字幕
because they're clearly iterating an identical number of times?
Was this a hand or just a stretch?
中文字幕
No, stretch.
So this is actually deliberate.
中文字幕
If I combine these, what would change logically in my program?
Yeah.
中文字幕
After every  input, you would ..
Yeah, so after every human input of a score,
中文字幕
I would see that user's chart, the row of hashes.
Then I'd ask them for another value.
中文字幕
They'd see the chart, another value, and they'd see the chart.
And that's fine, if that is the design you want.
中文字幕
Totally acceptable.
Totally correct.
中文字幕
I wanted mine to look a little more traditional with all of the bars
together, so I effectively had to postpone printing the hashes.
中文字幕
And that's why I did have a little bit of redundancy
by getting the user's input here and then iterating again
中文字幕
to actually print the user's output as a chart, so just a design decision.
Good question.
中文字幕
Other questions?
All right, so what does this look like?
中文字幕
Actually, you know what?
I can probably do a little better.
中文字幕
Let me open up one final example involving scores and this thing
called an array.
中文字幕
In Scores 4 here, let me go ahead and do this.
Now I've changed my chart function to do a little bit more,
中文字幕
and you might recall from week 0 and 1, we had the call function,
and we kept enhancing it to do more and more,
中文字幕
like putting more and more logic into it.
Notice this.
中文字幕
Chart function now takes a second argument, which is kind of interesting.
It takes one argument, which is a number,
中文字幕
and then the next argument is an array of scores.
So long story short, if you want to have a function that
中文字幕
takes as input an array, you don't have to know
in advance how big that array is.
中文字幕
You should not, in fact, put a number in between the square brackets
in this context.
中文字幕
But the thing is you do need to know, at some point,
how many items are in the array.
中文字幕
If you've programmed in Java, took AP CS, Java just gives you .length,
if you recall that feature of objects.
中文字幕
C does not have this.
Arrays do not have an inherent length associated with them.
中文字幕
You have to tell everyone who uses your array how long it is.
So even though you don't do that syntactically here,
中文字幕
you literally just say, I expect an argument called scores that
is an array per the square brackets.
中文字幕
You have to pass and almost always a second variable
that is literally called whatever you want,
中文字幕
but is the number of things in that array,
because if the goal of this function is just
中文字幕
to iterate over the number of scores that are passed in,
and then iterate over the number of points in that score
中文字幕
in order to print out the hashes, you need to know this count.
So what does this function do, just to be clear?
中文字幕
This iterates over the total number of scores from 0 to count,
which is probably 3 or 5 or whatever.
中文字幕
This loop here, using J, which is just a convention,
instead iterates from 0 to whatever that i-th score is.
中文字幕
So this is what's convenient.
Now I've passed in the array, and I can still get at individual values
中文字幕
just by using i, because I'm on my i-th iteration here.
So you might recall this from Mario, for instance, or any other example
中文字幕
in which you had nested loops--
just very conventional to use i on the outside, j on the inside.
中文字幕
But again, the only point here is that you can, indeed, pass around arrays,
even as arguments, which we'll see why that's useful before long.
中文字幕
Any questions?
OK, so this was a lot, but we can do so much more still with arrays.
中文字幕
It gets even more and more cool.
In fact, we'll see, in just a bit, how arrays have actually
中文字幕
been with us since last week.
We just didn't quite realize it under the hood, but let's go ahead
中文字幕
and take a breather, five minutes.
We'll come back and dive in.
中文字幕
All right.
So I know that was a bit of a cliffhanger.
中文字幕
Where else could arrays have actually been?
But, of course, this is how we might depict it pictorially.
中文字幕
We called it an array, and it turns out that last week, when
we introduced strings, strings, sequences of characters,
中文字幕
are literally just an array by another name.
A string is an array of chars, and chars, of course, is another data type.
中文字幕
Now what are the actual implications of this,
both in terms of representation, like how a computer's representing
中文字幕
information, and then fundamentally, programmatically,
what can we do when we know all of our data
中文字幕
is so back to back to back or so proximal to one another?
Well, it turns out that we can apply this logic in a few different ways.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and open up, for instance,
an example here called String 0.
中文字幕
So in our code for today, in our Source 2 folder,
let me go ahead and open up String 0, and this example looks like this.
中文字幕
Notice that we first, on line 9, get a string from the user.
Just say, input, please.
中文字幕
We store that value in a string, s, and then we say, here comes the output.
And notice what I'm doing in the following line.
中文字幕
I'm iterating over i from 0 to strlen, whatever that is.
And then in line 13, I'm printing a character one at a time.
中文字幕
But notice the syntax I'm using, which we didn't use last week.
If you have a string called s, you can index into a string
中文字幕
just like it's an array, because it, indeed, is underneath the hood.
So s bracket i, where i starts at 0 and goes
中文字幕
up to whatever this value is is just a way of getting character 0, then
character 1, then character 2, then character 3,
中文字幕
and so the end result is actually going to look like this.
Let me go ahead and do, make string--
中文字幕
whoops-- make string 0.
Oops.
中文字幕
Not in the directory.
Make string 0, ./string0, Enter, and I'll type in, say, Zamyla,
中文字幕
and the output now is Z-A-M-Y-L-A. It's a little messy,
because I don't have a new line here, so let me actually-- let's clean that up,
中文字幕
because this is unnecessarily sloppy.
So let me go ahead and print out a new line.
中文字幕
Let me recompile with make string 0, dot--
whoops-- ./string0.
中文字幕
Input shall be Zamyla, Enter, and now Z-A-M-Y-L-A.
So why is that happening?
中文字幕
Well, if I scroll down on this code, it seems that I am,
via this printf line here, just getting the i-th character of the name in s,
中文字幕
and then printing out one character at a time per the %c,
followed by a new line.
中文字幕
So you might guess, what is this function here doing?
Strlen-- slightly abbreviated, but you can, perhaps, glean what it means.
中文字幕
Yeah, so it's actually string length.
So it turns out there is a function that comes
中文字幕
with C called strlen, and humans back in the day
and to this day like to type as few characters when possible.
中文字幕
And so strlen is string length, and the way you use it is you
just need one more header file.
中文字幕
So there's another library, the so-called string
library that gives you string-related functions
中文字幕
beyond what CS50's library provides.
And so if you include string.h, that gives you access
中文字幕
to another function called strlen, that if you pass it,
a variable containing a string, it will pass you back
中文字幕
as a return value the total number of characters.
So I typed in Z-A-M-Y-L-A, and so that should be returning to me six,
中文字幕
thereby printing out the six characters in Zamyla's name.
Yeah.
中文字幕
Uh-huh.
useful to get the individual digits ..
中文字幕
Really good question.
In the credit problem of the problem set, would this have been useful?
中文字幕
Yes, absolutely.
But recall that in the credit pset, we encourage you to actually
中文字幕
take in the number as a long, so as an integral value, which
thereby necessitated arithmetic.
中文字幕
But yes, if you had, instead, in a problem involving credit card
numbers, gotten the human's input as a long string of characters
中文字幕
and not as an actual number like an int or a long,
then, yes, you could actually get at those individual characters,
中文字幕
which probably would have made things even easier but deliberate.
Yeah.
中文字幕
Really good question.
If we're defining string in CS50, are we redefining it in string?
中文字幕
No.
So string, even though it's named string.h,
中文字幕
doesn't actually define something called a string.
It just has string-related functions.
中文字幕
More on that soon.
Yeah.
中文字幕
individual values ??
Ah, really good question.
中文字幕
Could you edit the individual values?
So short answer, yes.
中文字幕
We could absolutely change values, and we'll soon do that in another context.
Other questions?
中文字幕
All right, so turns out this is correct, if my goal is
to print out all of the characters in Zamyla's name,
中文字幕
but it's not the best design.
And this one's a little subtle, but this is, again, what we mean by design.
中文字幕
And to a question that came up during the break,
did we expect everyone to be writing good style and good design last week?
中文字幕
No.
Up until today, like we've introduced the notion of correctness
中文字幕
in both Scratch and in C last week, but now we're
introducing these other axes of quality of code
中文字幕
like design, how well-designed it is, and how pretty
does it look in the context of style.
中文字幕
So expectations are here on out meant to be aligned with those characteristics,
but not in the past.
中文字幕
So there's a slight inefficiency here.
So on the first iteration of this loop, I first initialize i to 0,
中文字幕
and then I check if i less than the length of the string, which hopefully,
it is, if it's Zamyla, which is longer than 0.
中文字幕
Then I print the i-th character.
Then I increment i.
中文字幕
Then I check this condition.
Then I print the i-th character.
中文字幕
Then I increment i.
Then I check this condition and so forth.
中文字幕
We looped through loops last week, and you've used them, perhaps,
by now in problems.
中文字幕
What question am I redundantly asking seemingly unnecessarily?
I have to check a condition again and again,
中文字幕
because i is getting incremented.
But there's another other question that I
中文字幕
don't need to keep asking again just to get the same answer.
What is the length [? of the string? ?]
中文字幕
Yeah, there's this function call
in my loop of strlen s, which is fine.
中文字幕
This is correct.
I'm checking the length of the string, but once I type in Zamyla,
中文字幕
her name is not changing in length.
I'm incrementing i, so I'm moving in the string, if you will.
中文字幕
But the string itself, Z-A-M-Y-L-A, is not changing.
So why am I asking the computer, again and again, get me the strlen of s,
中文字幕
get me the strlen of s, get me the strlen of s.
So I can actually fix this.
中文字幕
I can improve the design, because that must take some amount of time.
Maybe it's fast, but it's still a non-zero amount of time.
中文字幕
So you know what I could do?
I could do something like this-- int n get string length of s.
中文字幕
And now just do this.
This would be better design, because now I'm only asking the question once
中文字幕
of the function.
I'm remembering or caching, if you will, the answer, and then
中文字幕
I'm just using a variable.
And just comparing variables is just faster
中文字幕
than comparing a variable against a function, which has to be called,
which has to return a value, which you can then compare.
中文字幕
But honestly, it doesn't have to be this verbose.
We can actually be a little elegant about this.
中文字幕
If you're using a loop, a secret feature of loops
is that you can have commas after declaring variables.
中文字幕
And you can actually do this and make this even more elegant, if you will,
or more confusing-looking, depending on your perspective.
中文字幕
But this now does the same thing but declares n inside of the loop,
just like I'm declaring i, and it's just a little tighter.
中文字幕
It's one fewer lines of code.
Any questions, then?
中文字幕
.
Good question.
中文字幕
In the way I've just done it cannot reuse this outside of the curly braces.
The scope of i and n exists only in this context right now.
中文字幕
The other way, yes.
I could have used it elsewhere.
中文字幕
What if you  other loops, and you also had ??
Absolutely.
中文字幕
Using different letters of the alphabet,
you could just use n and not be ..
中文字幕
Correct.
If I want to use the length of s again, absolutely.
中文字幕
I can declare the variable, as I did earlier, outside of the loop,
so as to reuse it.
中文字幕
That's totally fine.
Yes.
中文字幕
And even i-- i exists only inside of this loop, so if I have another loop,
I can reuse i, and it's a different i, because these variables only
中文字幕
exist inside the for loop in which they're declared.
So it turns out that these strings don't have anything in them
中文字幕
other than character after character after character.
And in fact, let me go ahead here and draw
中文字幕
a picture of what's actually going on underneath the hood of the computer
here.
中文字幕
So when I type in Zamyla's name, I'm, of course,
doing something like Z-A-M-Y-L-A. But where is that actually going?
中文字幕
Well, we know now that inside of your computer is RAM or memory,
and you can think of it like a grid.
中文字幕
And honestly, I can think of this whole screen
as just being in a different orientation, a grid of memory.
中文字幕
So for instance, maybe we can divide it into rows and columns like this, not
necessarily to scale, and there's more rows and columns.
中文字幕
So on the screen here, I'm just dividing things
into the individual bytes of memory that we saw a moment ago.
中文字幕
And so, indeed, underneath the hood of the computer is this layout of memory.
The compiler has somehow figured out or the program has somehow figured out
中文字幕
where to put the z and where the a and the m and the y and the l and the a,
but the key is that they're all contiguous, back to back to back.
中文字幕
But the catch is if I'm typing other words into my program or scores
into my program or any data into my program,
中文字幕
it's going to end up elsewhere in the computer's memory.
So how do you know where Zamyla begins and where
中文字幕
Zamyla ends, so to speak, in memory?
Well, the variable, called s, essentially is here.
中文字幕
There's some remembrance in the computer of where s begins.
But there's no obvious way to know where Zamyla ends,
中文字幕
unless we ourselves tell the computer.
So unbeknownst to us, any time a computer is storing a string like
中文字幕
Z-A-M-Y-L-A, it turns out that it's not using one, two, three, four, five,
six characters.
中文字幕
It's actually using seven secretly.
It's actually putting a special character
中文字幕
of all zeros in the very last bytes.
Every byte is eight bits, so it's putting secretly eight zeros there,
中文字幕
or we can actually draw this more conventionally as /0.
It's what's called the null character, and it just means all zeros.
中文字幕
So the length of the string, Zamyla, is six,
but how many bytes does it apparently take up, just to be clear?
中文字幕
So it actually takes up seven.
And this is kind of a secret implementation detail
中文字幕
that we don't really have to care about, but eventually, we will,
because if we want to implement certain functionality,
中文字幕
we're going to need to know what is actually going on.
So for instance, let me go ahead and do this.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and create a program called strlen itself.
So this is not a function but a program called strlen.c.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and include the CS50 library at the top.
Let me go ahead and include stdio.h.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and type out main void, so all this is same as always.
And then let me go ahead and prompt the user for, say, his or her name,
中文字幕
like so.
And then you know what?
中文字幕
Let me actually, this time, not just print their name out,
because we've done that ad nauseam.
中文字幕
Let's just count the number of letters in his or her name.
So how could we do that?
中文字幕
Well, we could just do this-- int n get strlen of s, and then say,
printf "The length of your name is %i."
中文字幕
And then we can plug in n, because that's
the number we stored the length in.
中文字幕
But to use strlen, I have to include what header file?
String.h, which is the new one, so string.h.
中文字幕
And now if I type this all correctly, make strlen, make strlen, good.
./strlen-- let's try it--
中文字幕
Zamyla.
Enter.
中文字幕
OK, the length of her name is six.
But what is strlen doing?
中文字幕
Well, strlen is just an abstraction for us that someone else wrote,
and it's wonderfully convenient, but you know, we don't strictly need it.
中文字幕
I can actually do this myself.
If I understand what the computer is doing,
中文字幕
I can implement this same functionality myself as follows.
I can declare a variable called n and initialize it to 0,
中文字幕
and then you know what?
I'm going to go ahead and do this.
中文字幕
While s bracket n does not equal all zeros,
but you don't write all zeros like this.
中文字幕
You literally do this--
that /0 to which I referred earlier in single quotes.
中文字幕
That just means all zeros in the bytes.
And now I can go ahead and do n++.
中文字幕
If I'm familiar with what this means, remember,
that this is just n equals n plus 1, but it's just a little more compact to say,
中文字幕
n++.
And then I can print out the name of your n--
中文字幕
the name of your n--
the name of-- the length of your name is %i, plugging in n.
中文字幕
So why does this work?
It's a little funky-looking, but this is just
中文字幕
demonstrating an understanding of what's going on
underneath the proverbial hood.
中文字幕
If n is initialized to zero, and I look at s bracket n,
well, that's like looking at s bracket 0.
中文字幕
And if the string, s, is Zamyla, what is s bracket 0?
Z. And then it does not equal /0.
中文字幕
It equals z, obviously.
So we increment n.
中文字幕
So now n is 1.
Now n is 1.
中文字幕
So what is s bracket 1 in Zamyla's name?
A and so forth, and we get to Z-A-M-Y-L-A, then all zeros,
中文字幕
the so-called null character, or /0.
That, of course, does equal /0, so the loop stops,
中文字幕
thereby leaving the total count or value of n at what it previously was,
which was 6.
中文字幕
So that's it.
Like all underneath the hood, all we have
中文字幕
is memory laid out like this, top to bottom, left to right,
and yet all of the functionality we've been using for a week now
中文字幕
and henceforth just boils down to some relatively simple primitives,
and if you understand those primitives, you
中文字幕
can do anything you want using the computer, both computationally
code-wise, but also memory-wise.
中文字幕
We can actually see, in fact, some of the stuff we looked at two weeks ago as
follows.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and open up an example called ASCII 0.
Recall that ASCII is the mapping between letters and numbers in a computer.
中文字幕
And notice what this program's going to do.
Make-- let me go into this folder.
中文字幕
Make ascii0, ./ascii0, Enter.
The string shall be, let's say, Zamyla, Enter.
中文字幕
Well, it turns out that if you actually look up
the ASCII code for Zamyla's name, z is 90, lowercase a is 97, m is 109,
中文字幕
and so forth.
There are those characters, and actually, we
中文字幕
can play the same game we did last week.
If I do this again on "hi," there's your 72, and there's your 73.
中文字幕
Where is this coming from?
Well, now that I know how to manipulate individual strings,
中文字幕
notice what I can do.
I can get a string from the user, just as we always have.
中文字幕
I can iterate over the length of that string, albeit inefficiently
using strlen here.
中文字幕
And then notice this new feature today.
I can now convert one data type to another, because a char,
中文字幕
a character is just eight bits, but presented in the context of characters.
Bytes is also just eight bits that you could treat as an integer, a number.
中文字幕
It's totally context-sensitive.
If you use Photoshop, it's a graphic.
中文字幕
If you use a text program, it's a message and so forth.
So you can encode--
中文字幕
change the context.
So notice here, s bracket i is, of course, the i-th character of Zamyla's
中文字幕
name, so Z or A or M or whatever.
But I can convert that i-th character to an integer doing what's called casting.
中文字幕
You can literally, in parentheses, specify the data type
you want to convert one data type to, and then
中文字幕
store it in exactly that data type.
So s bracket i-- convert it to a number.
中文字幕
Then store it in an actual number variable, so I can print out its value.
So c-- this is show me the character.
中文字幕
Show me the letter as by plugging in the character, and then the letter--
sorry, the character and the number that I've just converted it to.
中文字幕
And you don't actually even have to be explicit.
This is called explicit casting.
中文字幕
Technically, we can do this implicitly, too.
And the computer knows that numbers are characters,
中文字幕
and characters are a number.
You don't have to be so pedantic and even do
中文字幕
the explicit casting in parentheses.
You can just do it implicitly with data types, and honestly, at this point,
中文字幕
I don't even need the variable.
I can get rid of this, and down here, I can literally just
中文字幕
print the same thing twice, but tell printf
to print the first in the context of a character
中文字幕
and the second in the context of an int, just treating the exact same bits
differently.
中文字幕
That's implicit casting.
And it just demonstrates what we did in week 0
中文字幕
when we claimed that letters are numbers,
and numbers can also be colors, and colors can be images, and so forth.
中文字幕
Is this a question?
Would've been useful for credit.
中文字幕
Also, yes.
It all comes back to credit.
中文字幕
Yeah.
Indeed.
中文字幕
Other questions?
No.
中文字幕
All right, so what else can we actually do with this appreciation?
So super simple feature that all of us surely take for granted,
中文字幕
if we even use it anymore these days.
Google Docs, Microsoft Word, and such can automatically
中文字幕
capitalize words for you these days.
I mean your phone can do it nowadays.
中文字幕
They just sort of AutoCorrect your messages.
Well, how is that actually working?
中文字幕
Well, once you know that a string is just a bunch of characters
back to back to back, and you know that these characters have numbers
中文字幕
representing them, and like capital A is 65, and lowercase A is 97, apparently,
and so forth, we can leverage these patterns.
中文字幕
If I go ahead and open up this other example
here called Capitalize 0, notice what this program is
中文字幕
going to do for me first by running it.
Make capitalize 0 ./capitalize0.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and type in Zamyla's name just as before, but now
it's all capital.
中文字幕
So this is a little extreme.
Hopefully, your phone is not capitalizing every letter,
中文字幕
but you can imagine it capitalizing just the first, if you wanted it.
So how does this work?
中文字幕
Well, let me go ahead and open up this example here.
And so what we did--
中文字幕
so here, I'm getting a string from the user, just as we always do.
Then I'm saying, after, just to kind of format the output nicely.
中文字幕
Here, I'm doing a loop pretty efficiently from i equals 0 up
to the length of the string.
中文字幕
And now notice this neat application of logic.
It's a little cryptic, certainly, at first glance.
中文字幕
But whoops.
And now it's gone.
中文字幕
And what am I doing exactly with these lines of code?
Well, with every iteration of this loop, I'm asking the question,
中文字幕
is the i-th character of s, so the current character,
is it greater than or equal to lowercase A, and is it less than
中文字幕
or equal to lowercase Z?
Put another way, how do you say that more colloquially in English?
中文字幕
Is it lowercase, literally.
But this is the more programmatic way of expressing, is it lowercase?
中文字幕
All right, if it is, go ahead and do this.
Now this is a little funky, but print out a character, specifically
中文字幕
the i-th character, but subtract from that lowercase letter whatever
the difference is between little A and big A. Now where did that come from?
中文字幕
So it turns out--
OK, capital A is 65.
中文字幕
Lowercase A is 97.
So the difference between those is 32.
中文字幕
And that's true for B, so capital B is 66, and lowercase B is 98.
Still 32, and it repeats for the whole alphabet.
中文字幕
So I could just do this.
If I know that lowercase letters have bigger numbers, like 97, 98,
中文字幕
and I know that lowercase numbers have lower letters, like 65, 66,
I can just literally subtract off 32 from my lowercase letters.
中文字幕
As you point out, it's a lowercase letter.
Subtract 32, and that gives us what result?
中文字幕
The capitalized version.
It uppercases things for us.
中文字幕
But honestly, this feels a little hackish that, like, OK, yes,
I can do the math correctly, but you know what?
中文字幕
It's better practice, generally, to abstract this away.
Don't get into the weeds of counting how many characters are away
中文字幕
from each other.
Math is cheap and easy in the computer.
中文字幕
Let it do the math for you by subtracting whatever the value of A
is, of capital A is from the value of lowercase A. Or we could just write 32.
中文字幕
Otherwise, go ahead and just print the character unchanged.
So in this case, the A-M-Y-L-A in Zamyla's name got uppercased,
中文字幕
and everything else, the Z, got left alone,
just by understanding what's going on with how the computer's represented.
中文字幕
But honestly, God, I don't want to keep writing code like this.
Like, I'm never going to get this.
中文字幕
I'm new to programming, perhaps.
I'm never going to get this sort of sequence of all the cryptic symbols
中文字幕
together, and that's OK, because we can actually implement this same program
a little more easily, thanks to functions
中文字幕
and abstractions that others have written for us.
So in this program, turns out I can simplify
中文字幕
the questions I'm asking by literally calling a function that says, is lower.
And there's another one called, is upper,
中文字幕
and there's bunches of others that just literally are called,
is something or other.
中文字幕
So is lower takes an argument like the i-th character of s,
and it just returns a bull-- true or false.
中文字幕
How is it implemented?
Well, honestly, if we looked at the code that someone else wrote decades ago
中文字幕
for is upper, odds are-- or is lower--
odds are he or she wrote code that looks almost like this.
中文字幕
But we don't need to worry about that level of detail.
We can just use his or her function, but how do we do that?
中文字幕
Turns out that this function-- and you would only know this
by having been told or Googling or reading a reference--
中文字幕
is in a library called ctype.h.
And you need the header file called ctype.h in order to use it.
中文字幕
And we'll almost always point you to references and documentation
to explain that to you.
中文字幕
Toupper is another feature, right?
This math-- like, my god.
中文字幕
I just want to uppercase a letter.
I don't want to really keep thinking about how far apart uppercase letters
中文字幕
are from lowercase.
Turns out that in the C type library, there's
中文字幕
another function called toupper that literally does the exact same thing
in the previous program we wrote.
中文字幕
And so that, too, is OK.
But you know what?
中文字幕
This feels a little verbose.
It would be nice if I could really tighten this program up.
中文字幕
So how those toupper work?
Well, it turns out some of you might be familiar with CS50 Reference
中文字幕
Online, our web-based app that we have that
helps you navigate available functions in C.
中文字幕
Turns out that all of the data for that application
comes from an older command line program that comes in Linux
中文字幕
and comes in the sandbox called Man for manual.
And anytime you type "man" at the command prompt, and then the name
中文字幕
of a function you're interested in, if it exists,
it will tell you a little something about it.
中文字幕
So if I go to toupper, man toupper, I get slightly cryptic documentation
here.
中文字幕
But notice, toupper and some other functions
convert uppercase or lowercase.
中文字幕
That's the summary.
Notice that in the synopsis, the man page, so to speak,
中文字幕
is telling me what header file I have to include.
Notice that under Synopsis, it's also telling me
中文字幕
what the signature or prototype is of the function.
In other words, the documentation in Man, the Linux programmer's manual,
中文字幕
is very terse.
So it's not going to hold your hand in this black and white format.
中文字幕
It's just going to convey, well, implicitly,
you better put this on top of your file.
中文字幕
And by the way, this is how you use the function.
It takes an argument called C, returns a value of type int.
中文字幕
Why is it int?
Let me wave my hands at that.
中文字幕
It effectively returns a character for our purposes today.
And if we scroll down, OK, description.
中文字幕
Ugh, I don't really want to read all of this, but OK, here we go.
If c is a lowercase letter, toupper returns its uppercase equivalent,
中文字幕
if an uppercase representation exists in the current locale.
That just means if it's punctuation, it's not going to do anything.
中文字幕
Otherwise, it returns C, And that's kind of the key detail.
If I pass it lowercase A, it's going to give me capital A,
中文字幕
but if I pass it capital A, what's it going to give me?
Capital A.
中文字幕
Also, capital A. It returns the original character, c.
That's the only detail I cared about.
中文字幕
When in doubt, read the manual.
And it might be a little cryptic, and this
中文字幕
is why CS50 Reference takes somewhat cryptic documentation
and tries to simplify it into more human-friendly terms.
中文字幕
But at the end of the day, these are the authoritative answers.
And if I or one of the staff don't know, we literally
中文字幕
pull up the Man page or CS50 Reference to answer these kinds of questions.
Now what's the implication?
中文字幕
I don't need any of this.
I can literally get rid of the condition and just let
中文字幕
toupper do all of the legwork, and now my program
is so much more compact than the previous versions were,
中文字幕
because I've read the documentation.
I know what the function does, and I can let toupper uppercase something
中文字幕
or just pass it through unchanged.
We can better design, because we're writing fewer lines of code that
中文字幕
are just as clear, and so we can now actually tighten things up.
Any questions on this particular approach?
中文字幕
All right.
So we're getting very low level.
中文字幕
Now let's make these things more useful, because clearly, other people
have solved some of these problems for us,
中文字幕
as by having these functions and the C type library and the string library.
What more is there?
中文字幕
Well, recall that every time we run Clang, or even run make,
we're typing multiple words at the command prompt.
中文字幕
You're typing make hello or make Mario, a second word,
or you're typing clang-o, hello, hello.c,
中文字幕
like lots of words at the prompt.
Well, it turns out that all this time, you're using, indeed,
中文字幕
command line arguments.
But in C, you can write programs that also accept words and numbers when
中文字幕
the user runs the program.
Think back, after all.
中文字幕
When you ran Mario, you did ./mario, Enter.
You couldn't type any more words at the prompt.
中文字幕
When you did credit, you did ./credit, Enter.
No more words at the prompt.
中文字幕
You used get string or get long to get more input, but not
at the command line.
中文字幕
And it turns out that we can, relatively simply, in C,
but it's a little cryptic at first glance.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and--
let me go ahead and, here, pull up this signature here, which looks like this.
中文字幕
This is the function that we're all used to by now for writing a main function.
And up until now, we've said void.
中文字幕
Main doesn't take any inputs, and indeed, it just runs.
But it turns out if you change your existing programs or future programs,
中文字幕
not to say void, but to say, int argc, string argv,
it's a little cryptic at first glance.
中文字幕
But what's a recognizable symbol now?
Yeah, there's brackets here.
中文字幕
So it turns out that every time you write a program,
if you don't just say void, you actually enable this feature
中文字幕
by writing int argc, string argv.
You can actually tell Clang, you know what?
中文字幕
I want this program to accept one or more words or numbers after the name
of the program, so I can do ./hellodavid, or ./hellozamyla.
中文字幕
I don't have to wait for the program to be running to use string.
And just as with the earlier example, where you were able to chart an array,
中文字幕
main is defined as taking an array, called argv historical reasons--
argument vector.
中文字幕
Vector means array.
Argument vector, bracket, closed bracket just means this is--
中文字幕
this contains one or more words, each of which is a string.
Argc is argument count, so this is the variable
中文字幕
that main gets access to that tells it how many arguments,
how many strings are actually in argv.
中文字幕
So how can we use this in a useful way?
Well, let me go ahead here and open up the sandbox.
中文字幕
And let me go ahead and create a new file called, say, argv0, argv0.c--
again, argument vector, just list or array of arguments.
中文字幕
And let me go ahead and, as usual, include cs50.h, include stdio.h,
and then int main not void, but int argc, string argv--
中文字幕
argv-- open bracket, closed bracket.
And even if that doesn't come naturally at first, it will eventually.
中文字幕
And I'm going to do this.
If the number of arguments passed in equals 2,
中文字幕
then I'm going to go ahead and do this-- printf, hello %s, comma,
and here in the past, I've typed a variable name.
中文字幕
And I now actually have access to a variable.
Go ahead and do argv bracket 1.
中文字幕
Else, if the user does not type, apparently, two words,
let me go ahead and just by default, say, hello world, as we always have.
中文字幕
Now why-- what is this doing, and how is it doing it?
Well, let's quickly run it.
中文字幕
So make-- whoops.
Make argv0, ./argv0, Enter, Hello World.
中文字幕
But if I do Hello--
or dot-- the program would be better named
中文字幕
if we called it Hello, but Zamyla, Enter.
Hello Zamyla.
中文字幕
If I change it to David, now I have access to David.
If I had David Malan, no.
中文字幕
It doesn't support that.
So what's going on?
中文字幕
If you change main in any program write to take
these two arguments, argc and argv of type string int
中文字幕
and then an array of strings, argc tells you how many words
were typed at the prompt.
中文字幕
So if the human typed two words, I presume
the first word is the name of the program, dot slash argv0,
中文字幕
the second word is presumably my name, if he or she is actually
providing their name at the prompt.
中文字幕
And so I print out argv bracket 1.
Not 0 because that's the name of the program, but argv bracket 1.
中文字幕
Else, down here, if the human doesn't provide just Zamyla, or just David,
or just one word more generally, I just print the default, "Hello world."
中文字幕
But what's neat about this now is notice that argv is an array of strings.
What is a string?
中文字幕
It's an array of characters.
And so let's enter just one last piece of syntax that gets kind of powerful
中文字幕
here.
Let me go ahead and do this.
中文字幕
Let me go ahead and, in a new file here, argv 1 dot c.
Let me go ahead and paste this in.
中文字幕
Close this.
Let me go ahead and do this.
中文字幕
Rather than do this logical checking, let me do this, for--
let's say for int, i get 0.
中文字幕
i is less than argc--
i++.
中文字幕
Let's go ahead and, one per line, print out every word
that the human just typed, just to reinforce
中文字幕
that this is indeed what's going on.
So argv bracket 0, save.
中文字幕
Make argv 1, enter.
And now let's go ahead and run this program--
中文字幕
dot slash, argv 1, David Malan.
OK, you see all three words.
中文字幕
If we change it to Zamyla, we see just those two words.
If we change it to Zamyla Chan, we see those three words.
中文字幕
So we clearly have access to all of the words in the array,
but let's take this one step further.
中文字幕
Rather than just print out every word in a string, let's go ahead and do this.
For intj get 0.
中文字幕
n equals the string length of the current argument, like this--
j is less than n, j++--
中文字幕
oops, oops, oops-- j++.
Now let me go ahead and print out not the full string, but let me do-- oops,
中文字幕
oops-- let me go ahead and print out this--
not a string, but a character, n bracket i bracket j, like this.
中文字幕
All right.
So what's going on?
中文字幕
One, this outer loop, and let's comment it, iterate over strings in argv.
This inner loop, iterate over chars in argv bracket i.
中文字幕
So the outer loop iterates over all of the strings in argv.
And the inner loop, using a different variable, starting at 0,
中文字幕
iterates over all of the characters in the ith
argument, which itself is a string.
中文字幕
So we can call string length on it.
And then we do this up until n, which is the length of that string.
中文字幕
And then we print out each character.
So just to be clear-- when I run arv1 and correct it, at first glance,
中文字幕
why it's implicitly declaring library function sterling, what's almost always
the solution when you do this wrong?
中文字幕
Yeah.
So I forgot this, so include string.h and help50 would
中文字幕
help with that as well.
Let's recompile with make argv1.
中文字幕
All right.
When I run argv1, of, say, Zamyla Chan, what am I going to see?
中文字幕
Yeah.
Is that the right intuition?
中文字幕
I'm going to see Zamyla Chan, but--
One character on each line, including the program's name.
中文字幕
So in fact, let me scroll this up so it's a little bigger.
Enter.
中文字幕
OK, it's a little stupid, the program, but it does confirm that using arrays
do I have access not only to the words, but I can kind of
中文字幕
have the second dimension.
And within each word, I can get at each character within.
中文字幕
And we do this, again, just by using not just single square brackets,
but double.
中文字幕
And again, just break this down into the first principles.
What is this first bracket?
中文字幕
This is the ith argument, the ith string in the array.
And then if you take it further, with bracket j,
中文字幕
that gives you the j character inside of this.
Now, who cares about any of this kind of functionality?
中文字幕
Well, let me scroll back and propose one application here.
So recall that CS is really just problem solving.
中文字幕
But suppose the problem that you want to solve
is to actually pass a secret message in class
中文字幕
or send someone a secret for whatever reason.
Well, the input to that problem is generally
中文字幕
called plain test, a message you want to send to that other person.
You ideally want ciphertext to emerge from it,
中文字幕
which is enciphered and scrambled, somehow encrypted information
so that anyone in the room, like the teacher, can't just grab the note
中文字幕
and read what you're sending to your secret crush or love across the room,
or in any other context as well.
中文字幕
But the problem is that if the message you want to send, say,
is our old friend Hi!, with an exclamation point,
中文字幕
you can encode it in certain contexts as just 72, 73, 33.
And I daresay most classes on campus if you wrote on a piece of paper 72,
中文字幕
73, 33, passed it through the room, and whatever professor intercepts it,
they're not going to know what you're saying anyway.
中文字幕
But this is not a good system.
This is not a cryptosystem.
中文字幕
Why?
It's not secure.
中文字幕
Yeah.
Anyone has access to this, right, so long
中文字幕
as you attend like week 1 or 0 of CS50, or you just
have general familiarity with Ascii.
中文字幕
Like this is just a code.
I mean Ascii is a system that maps letters to numbers.
中文字幕
And anyone else who knows this code obviously
knows what your message is, because it's not a unique secret
中文字幕
to you and the recipient.
So that's probably not the best idea.
中文字幕
Well, you can be a little more sophisticated.
And this is back-- actually, a photograph
中文字幕
from World War I of a message that was sent from Germany to Mexico
that was encoded in a very similar way.
中文字幕
It wasn't using Ascii.
The numbers, as you can perhaps glean from the photo,
中文字幕
are actually much larger.
But in this system, in a militaristic context, there was a code book.
中文字幕
So similar in spirit to Ascii, where you have
a column of numbers and a column of letters to which they correspond,
中文字幕
a codebook more generally has like numbers, and then maybe
even letters or whole words that they correspond to,
中文字幕
sometimes thousands of them, like literally a really big book of codes.
And so long as only, in this context the Germans and the recipients,
中文字幕
the Mexicans, had access to that same book,
only they could encrypt and decrypt, or rather encode and decode information.
中文字幕
Of course, in this very specific context--
you can read more about this in historical texts--
中文字幕
this was intercepted.
This message, seemingly innocuous, though definitely
中文字幕
suspicious looking with all these numbers,
so therefore not innocuous, the British, in this case actually, intercepted it.
中文字幕
And thanks to a lot of efforts and cryptanalysis,
the Bletchley Park style code breaking, albeit further back,
中文字幕
were they able to figure out what those numbers represented in words
and actually decode the message.
中文字幕
And in fact, here's a photograph of some of the words
that were translated from one to the other.
中文字幕
But more on that in any online or textual references.
Turns out in this poem too there was a similar code, right?
中文字幕
So apropos of being in Boston here, you might recall this one.
"Listen my children, and you shall hear of the midnight ride of Paul Revere.
中文字幕
On the 18th of April in '75, hardly a man
is now alive who remembers that famous day and year.
中文字幕
He said to his friend, if the British march by land or sea
from the town tonight night, hang a lantern
中文字幕
aloft in the belfry arch of the North Church tower as a signal light,
one if by land, and two if by sea.
中文字幕
And I on the opposite shore will be ready to ride and spread
the alarm through every Middlesex village and farm for the country folk
中文字幕
to be up and to arm."
So it turns out some of that is not actually factually correct,
中文字幕
but the one if by land and the two if by sea code were
sort of an example of a one-time code.
中文字幕
Because if the revolutionaries in the American Revolution kind of
decided secretly among themselves literally that-- we will put up one
中文字幕
light at the top of a church if the British are coming by land.
And we will instead use two if the British are instead coming by sea.
中文字幕
Like that is a code.
And you could write it down in a book, unless you have a code book.
中文字幕
But of course, as soon as someone figures out that pattern,
it's compromised.
中文字幕
And so code books tend not to be the most robust mechanisms
for encoding information.
中文字幕
Instead, it's better to use something more algorithmic.
And wonderfully, in computer science is this black box
中文字幕
to-- we keep saying, the home of algorithms.
And in general, encryption is a problem with inputs and outputs,
中文字幕
but we just need one more input.
The input is what's generally called the key, or a secret.
中文字幕
And a secret might just be a number.
So for instance, if I wanted my secret to be 1,
中文字幕
because we'll keep the example simple, but it could really be any number.
And indeed, we saw with the photograph a moment ago,
中文字幕
the Germans used much larger than this, albeit in the context of codes.
Suppose that you now want to send a more private message to someone
中文字幕
across the room in a class that, I love you.
How do you go about encoding that in a way that isn't just using Ascii
中文字幕
and isn't just using some simple code book?
Well, let me propose that now that we understand how strings are represented,
中文字幕
right-- we're about to make love really, really lame and geeky--
so now that you know how to express strings computationally,
中文字幕
well, let's just start representing "I love you" in Ascii.
So I is 73.
中文字幕
L is 76.
O-V-E Y-O-U. That's just Ascii.
中文字幕
Should not send it this way, because anyone
who knows Ascii is going to know what you're saying.
中文字幕
But what if I enciphered this message, I performed an algorithm on it?
And at its simplest, an algorithm can just
中文字幕
be math-- simple arithmetic, as we've seen.
So you know, let me just use my secret key of 1.
中文字幕
And let me make sure that my crush knows that I am using a secret value of 1.
So he or she also knows to expect that value.
中文字幕
And before I send my message, I'm going to add 1 to every letter.
So 73 becomes 74.
中文字幕
76 becomes 77.
80, 87, 70, 90, 80, 86.
中文字幕
Now this could just be sent in the clear.
But then, I could actually send it as a textual message.
中文字幕
So let's convert it back to Ascii.
74 is now J. 77 is now M. 80 is now P. And you can perhaps see the pattern.
中文字幕
This message was, I love you.
And now, all of the letters are off by one, I think.
中文字幕
I became J. L became M. O became P, and so forth.
So now the claim would be, cryptographically, I'm
中文字幕
going to send this message across the room.
And now no one who has a code book is going to be able to solve this.
中文字幕
I can't just steal the book and decode it,
because now the key is only up here, so to speak.
中文字幕
It's just the number 1 that he or she and I
had to agree upon in advance that we would
中文字幕
use for sending our secret messages.
So if someone captures this message, teacher in the room or whoever,
中文字幕
how would they even go about decoding this or decrypting it?
Are there any techniques available to them?
中文字幕
I daresay we can kind of chip away at this love note.
What's that?
中文字幕
Guess and check.
OK, we could try all--
中文字幕
there still kind of some spacing.
So you know honestly, we could do like kind of a cryptanalysis of it,
中文字幕
a frequency attack.
Like, I can't think of too many words in English
中文字幕
that have a single letter in them.
So what does J probably represent?
中文字幕
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
I, probably.
中文字幕
Maybe A, but probably I. And there's not too many other options.
So we've attacked one part of the message already.
中文字幕
I see a commonality.
There's two what in here?
中文字幕
Two P. And I don't necessarily know that that maps to O, but I do
know it's the same character.
中文字幕
So if I kind of continue this thoughtful process or this trial and error,
and I figure out, oh, what if that's an O?
中文字幕
And then that's an O. And then wait a minute.
They're passing from one to another.
中文字幕
Maybe this says, I love you.
Like you actually can, with some probability,
中文字幕
decrypt a message by doing this kind of analysis on it.
It's at least more secure than the code book,
中文字幕
because you're not compromised if the book itself is stolen.
And you can change the key every time, so long as you
中文字幕
and the recipient actually agree on something.
But at least we now have this mechanism in place.
中文字幕
So with just the understanding of what you can do with strings,
can you actually now do really interesting domain-specific things
中文字幕
to them?
And in fact, back in the day, Caesar, back in militaristic times literally
中文字幕
used a cipher quite like this.
And frankly, when you're the first one to use these ciphers,
中文字幕
they actually are kind of secure, even if they're relatively simple.
But hopefully, not just using a key of 1, maybe 2, or 13, or 25,
中文字幕
or something larger.
But this is an example of a substitution cipher,
中文字幕
or a rotational cipher where everything's kind of rotating--
A's becoming B, B's becoming C. Or you can kind of
中文字幕
rotate it even further than that.
Well, let's take a look at one last example here
中文字幕
of just one other final primitive of a feature
today, before we then go back high level to bring everything together.
中文字幕
It turns out that printing out error messages
is not the only way to signal that something has gone wrong.
中文字幕
There's a new keyword, a new use of an old keyword in this example,
that's actually a convention for signaling errors.
中文字幕
So this is an example called exit.c.
It apparently wants the human to do what, if you infer from the code?
中文字幕
Exit .
Yes.
中文字幕
Say again?
Well, it wants the-- well, what
中文字幕
does it what the human to do implicitly, based on the printf's here?
How should I run this program?
中文字幕
Yeah?
just apply ..
中文字幕
Yeah.
So for whatever reason, this program implicitly
中文字幕
wants me to write exactly two words at the prompt.
Because if I don't, it's going to yell at me, missing command line argument.
中文字幕
And then it's going to return 1, whatever that is.
Otherwise, it's going to say, Hello, such and such.
中文字幕
So if I actually run this program--
let me go back over here and do make exit--
中文字幕
oops-- in my directory, make exit.
OK, dot slash exit, enter, I'm missing a command line argument.
中文字幕
All right, let me put Zamyla's name.
Oh, Hello Zamyla.
中文字幕
Let me put Zamyla Chan.
Nope, missing command line argument.
中文字幕
It just wants the one, so in this case here.
I'm seeing visually the error message, but it turns out
中文字幕
the computer is also signaling to me what the so-called exit code is.
So long story short, we've already seen examples last week of how
中文字幕
you can have a function return a value.
And we saw how [? Erin ?] came up on stage,
中文字幕
and she returned to me a piece of paper with a string on it.
But it turns out that main is a little special.
中文字幕
If main returns a value like 1 or 0, you can actually see that,
albeit in a kind of a non-obvious way.
中文字幕
If I run exit, and I run it correctly with Zamyla as the name,
if I then type echo, dollar sign, question mark, of all things,
中文字幕
enter, I will then see exactly what main returned with, which in this case is 0.
Now, let me try and be uncooperative.
中文字幕
If I actually run just dot slash exit, with no word,
I see, missing command line argument.
中文字幕
But if I do the same cryptic command, echo, dollar sign, question mark,
I see that main exited with 1.
中文字幕
Now, why is this useful?
Well, as we start to write more complicated programs,
中文字幕
it's going to be a convention to exit from main by returning
a non-zero value, if anything goes wrong.
中文字幕
0 happens to mean everything went well.
And in fact, in all of the programs we've
中文字幕
written thus far, if you don't mention return anything,
main automatically for you returns 0.
中文字幕
And it has been all this time.
It's just a feature, so you don't have to bother typing it yourself.
中文字幕
But what's nice about this, or what's real about this,
is if on your Mac or PC, if you've ever gotten an annoying error message that
中文字幕
says, error negative 29, system error has occurred, or something freezes,
but you very often see numbers on the screen, maybe.
中文字幕
Like those error codes actually tend to map to these kinds of values.
So when a human is writing software and something goes wrong
中文字幕
and an error happens, they typically return a value like this.
And the computer has access to it.
中文字幕
And this isn't all that useful for the human running the program.
But as your programs get more complex, we'll
中文字幕
see that this is actually quite useful as a way of signaling
that something indeed went wrong.
中文字幕
Whew.
OK, that's a lot of syntax wrapped in some loving context.
中文字幕
Any questions before we look at one final domain?
No?
中文字幕
All right.
So it turns out that we can answer the "who cares" question in yet another way
中文字幕
too.
It turns out-- let me go ahead and open up an example of our array again here--
中文字幕
that arrays can actually now be used to solve problems more algorithmically.
And this is where life gets more interesting.
中文字幕
Like we were so incredibly in the weeds today.
And as we move forward in the class, we're
中文字幕
not going to spend so much time on syntax,
and dollar signs, and question marks, and square brackets, and the like.
中文字幕
That's not the interesting part.
The interesting part is when we now have these fundamental building
中文字幕
blocks, like an array, with which we can solve problems.
So it turns out that an array, you know, you
中文字幕
can kind of think of it as a series of lockers,
a series of lockers that might look like this, inside of which
中文字幕
are values-- strings, or numbers, or chars, or whatnot.
But the lockers is an apt metaphor because a computer, unlike us humans,
中文字幕
can only see and do one thing at a time.
It can open one locker and look inside, but it can't kind of
中文字幕
take a step back, like we humans can, and look at all of the lockers,
even if all of the doors are open.
中文字幕
So it has to be a more deliberate act than that.
So what are the actual implications?
中文字幕
Well, all this time--
we had that phone book example in the first week,
中文字幕
and the efficiency of that algorithm, of finding Mike Smith in this phone book,
all assumed what feature of this phone book?
中文字幕
That it's ordered alphabetically.
That it was ordered alphabetically.
中文字幕
And that was a huge plus, because then I could go to the middle,
and I could go to the middle of the middle, and so forth.
中文字幕
And that was an algorithmic possibility.
On our phones, if you pull up your contacts,
中文字幕
you've got a list of first names, or last names, all alphabetically sorted.
That is because, guess what data structure or layout
中文字幕
your phone probably uses to store your contacts?
It's an array of some sort, right?
中文字幕
It's just a list.
And it might be displayed vertically, instead of horizontally,
中文字幕
as I've been drawing it today.
But it's just values that are back, to back, to back, to back, to back,
中文字幕
that are actually sorted.
But how did they actually get into that sorted order?
中文字幕
And how do you actually find values?
Well, let's consider what this problem is actually
中文字幕
like for a computer, as follows.
Let me go ahead here.
中文字幕
Would a volunteer mind joining us up here?
I can throw in a free stress ball.
中文字幕
OK, someone from the back?
OK, come on up here.
中文字幕
Come on.
What's your name?
中文字幕
ERIC: Eric.
Aaron.
中文字幕
All right.
So Aaron's going to come on up.
中文字幕
And--
ERIC: Eric.
中文字幕
I'm sorry?
Oh, Eric.
中文字幕
Nice to meet you.
All right.
中文字幕
Come on over here.
So Eric, now normally, I would ask you to find the number 23.
中文字幕
But seeing is that's a little easy, can you go ahead and just find us
the number 50 behind these doors, or really these yellow lockers?
中文字幕
8?
Nope.
中文字幕
42?
Nope.
中文字幕
OK.
Pretty good.
中文字幕
That's three, three out of seven.
How did you get it so quickly?
中文字幕
ERIC: I guessed.
OK, so he guessed.
中文字幕
Is that the best algorithm that Eric could have used here?
ERIC: Probably not.
中文字幕
Well, I don't know.
Yes?
中文字幕
No?
Yeah.
中文字幕
Why?
Why yes?
中文字幕
He has no other information.
So yes, like that was the best you can do.
中文字幕
But let me give you a little more information.
You can stay here.
中文字幕
And let me go ahead and reload the screen here.
And let me go ahead and pull up a different set of doors.
中文字幕
And now suppose that, much like the phone book, and much like the phones
are sorted, now these doors are sorted.
中文字幕
And find us the number 50.
All right.
中文字幕
So good.
What did you do that time?
中文字幕
Well, .
It was 50 is 116.
中文字幕
So I just--
Right.
中文字幕
So you jumped to the middle, initially, and then to the right half.
And then technically-- so we're technically off by 1, right?
中文字幕
Because like binary search would have gone to the middle of the--
that's OK, but very well done to Eric.
中文字幕
Here, let me at least reinforce this with a stress ball.
So thank you.
中文字幕
Very well done.
So with that additional information, as you know,
中文字幕
Eric was able to do better because the information was sorted on the screen.
But he only had one insight to a locker at a time,
中文字幕
because only by revealing what's inside can he actually see it.
So this seems to suggest that once you do
中文字幕
have this additional information in Eric's example, in your phone example,
in the phone book example, you open up possibilities for much much, much more
中文字幕
efficient algorithms.
But to get there, we've kind of been deferring this whole time in class
中文字幕
how you actually sort these elements.
And if you wouldn't mind-- and this way, we'll hopefully end on a more energized
中文字幕
note here because I know we've been in the weeds for a while--
can we get like eight volunteers?
中文字幕
OK, so 1, 2, 3, 4-- how about 5, 6, 7, 8, come on down.
Oh, I'm sorry.
中文字幕
Did I completely overlook the front row?
OK.
中文字幕
All right, next time.
Next time.
中文字幕
Come on down.
Oh, and Colton, do you mind meeting them over there instead?
中文字幕
All right.
Come on up.
中文字幕
What's your name?
[? CAHMY: ?] [? Cahmy. ?]
中文字幕
[? Cahmy? ?] David.
Right over there.
中文字幕
What's your name?
MATT: Matt.
中文字幕
Matt?
David.
中文字幕
[? JUHE: ?] [? Juhe. ?]
[? Juhe? ?] David.
中文字幕
MAX: Max.
Max, nice to meet you.
中文字幕
JAMES: James.
James, nice to see you.
中文字幕
Here, I'll get more chairs.
What's your name?
中文字幕
,PEYTON: Peyton.
Peyton?
中文字幕
David.
And two more.
中文字幕
Actually can what have you come down to this end here?
What's your name.
中文字幕
ANDREA: Andrea.
Andrea, nice to see you.
中文字幕
And your name?
[? PICCO: ?] [? Picco. ?]
中文字幕
[? Picco, ?] David.
Nice to see you.
中文字幕
OK, Colton has a T-shirt for each of you, very Harvard-esque here.
And each of these shirts, as you're about to see, has a number on it.
中文字幕
And that number is--
well, go ahead put them on, if you wouldn't mind.
中文字幕
OK, thank you so much.
So I daresay we've arranged our humans much like the lockers in an array.
中文字幕
Like we have humans back, to back, to back, to back.
But this is actually both a blessing and a constraint,
中文字幕
because we only have eight chairs.
So there's really not much room here, so we're confined to just this space here.
中文字幕
And I see we have a 4, 8, 5, 2, 3, 1, 6, 7.
So this is great.
中文字幕
Like they are unsorted.
By definition, it's pretty random.
中文字幕
So that's great.
So let's just start off like this.
中文字幕
Sort yourselves from 1 to 8, please.
OK.
中文字幕
All right.
Well, what algorithm was that?
中文字幕
[LAUGHTER]
Look around, figure it out.
中文字幕
OK, well--
MATT: Human ingenuity.
中文字幕
Human ingenuity?
Very well done.
中文字幕
So can we-- well, what was like a thought
going through any of your minds?
中文字幕
MATT: Find a chair and sit down.
Find the chair--
中文字幕
find the right chair.
So go to a location.
中文字幕
Good.
So like an index location, right?
中文字幕
Arrays have indices, so to spea--
0, 1, 2, all the way up to 7.
中文字幕
And even though our shirts are numbered from 1 to 8,
you can think in terms of 0 to 7.
中文字幕
So that was good.
Anyone else?
中文字幕
Other thoughts?
[? CAHMY: ?] I mean, this is something we implicitly think of,
中文字幕
but no one told us that it was ordered right to left.
Like we could have done it left to right.
中文字幕
OK.
Absolutely.
中文字幕
Could have gone from right to left, instead of left to right.
But at least we all agreed on this convention
中文字幕
too, so that was in your mind.
OK.
中文字幕
So good.
So we got this sorted.
中文字幕
Go ahead and re-randomize yourself, if you could.
And what algorithm was this?
中文字幕
Just random awkwardness?
OK, so that's fine.
中文字幕
So it looks pretty random.
That will do.
中文字幕
Let's see if we can now reduce the process of sorting
to something a little more algorithmic so that, one, we can be sure
中文字幕
we're correct and not just kind of get lucky that everyone kind of figured it
out and no one was left out, and two, then
中文字幕
start to think about how efficient it is, right?
Because if we've been gaining so much efficiency for the phone book,
中文字幕
for our contacts, for [? error ?] coming up,
we really should have been asking the whole time,
中文字幕
sure, you save time with binary search and divide and conquer,
but how much did it cost you to get to a point
中文字幕
where you can use binary search and divide and conquer?
Because sorting, if it's super, super, super expensive and time-consuming
中文字幕
maybe it's a net negative.
And you might as well just search the whole list,
中文字幕
rather than ever sort anything.
All right.
中文字幕
So let's see here.
6 and 5, I don't like this.
中文字幕
Why?
6 is supposed to come after 5.
中文字幕
And so, can we fix this, please?
All right.
中文字幕
And then let's see.
OK, 6 and 1-- ugh, don't really like this.
中文字幕
Yeah, can we fix this?
Very nice.
中文字幕
6 and 3, OK, you really got the short end of the stick here.
So 6 and 3, could we fix this?
中文字幕
And 6-- yeah, OK.
Ooh, OK, 6 and 7-- good.
中文字幕
All right, so that's pretty good.
7 and 8, nice.
中文字幕
8 and 4, sorry.
Could we switch here?
中文字幕
All right.
And then 8 and 2?
中文字幕
OK, could we switch here?
OK.
中文字幕
And let me ask you a somewhat rhetorical question.
OK, am I done?
中文字幕
OK, no.
Obviously not, but I did fix some problems, right?
中文字幕
I fixed some transpositions, numbers being out of order.
And in fact, I-- what's your name again?
中文字幕
[? CAHMY: ?] [? Cahmy. ?]
[? Cahmy, ?] kind of bubbled to the right here, if you will.
中文字幕
Like you were kind of farther down, and now you're over here.
And like the smaller numbers, kind of-- yeah 1.
中文字幕
Like, my god, like he kind of bubbled his way this way.
So things are percolating, in some sense.
中文字幕
And that's a good thing.
And so you know what?
中文字幕
Let Me try to fix some remaining problems.
So 1 and 5-- good.
中文字幕
Oh 3 and 5, could you switch?
5 and 6, OK.
中文字幕
6 and 7?
7 and 4, could you switch?
中文字幕
OK.
And 7 and 2, could you switch?
中文字幕
And now, I don't have to speak with [? Cahmy ?] again,
because we know you're in the right place.
中文字幕
So I actually don't have to do quite as much work
this time, which is kind of nice.
中文字幕
But am I done?
No, obviously not.
中文字幕
But what's the pattern now?
Like what's the fundamental primitive?
中文字幕
If I just compare pairwise humans and numbers,
I can slightly improve the situation each time
中文字幕
by just swapping them, swapping them.
And each time now--
中文字幕
I'm sorry, [? Picco ?] is in number 7's place.
I don't have to talk to him anymore, because he's now bubbled
中文字幕
his way all the way up to the top.
So even though I'm doing the same thing again and again,
中文字幕
and looping again and again isn't always the best thing,
so long as you're looping fewer and fewer times, I will eventually stop,
中文字幕
it would seem.
Because 6 is going to eventually go in the right place, and then 5,
中文字幕
and then 4, and so forth.
So if we can just finish this algorithm.
中文字幕
Good.
Not good.
中文字幕
OK, 6 and 2, not good.
If you could swap?
中文字幕
OK, and what's your name again?
PEYTON: Peyton.
中文字幕
Peyton is now in the right place.
I have even less work now ahead of me.
中文字幕
So if I can just continue this process--
1 and 3, 3 and 5, 4 and 5, OK, and then 2 and 5.
中文字幕
And then, what's your name again?
MATT: Matt.
中文字幕
Matt is now in the right place.
Even less work.
中文字幕
We're almost there.
1 and 3, 3 and 4, 4 and 2, if you could swap.
中文字幕
OK, almost done.
And 1 and 3, 3 and 2, if you could swap.
中文字幕
Nice.
So this is interesting.
中文字幕
It would seem that-- you know, in the first place,
I kind of compared seven pairs of people.
中文字幕
And then the next time I went through, I compared how many pairs of people
maximally?
中文字幕
Just six, right?
Because we were able to leave [? Cahmy ?] out.
中文字幕
And then we were able to leave [? Picco ?] out, and then Peyton.
And so the number of comparisons I was doing was getting fewer and fewer.
中文字幕
So that feels pretty good.
But you know what?
中文字幕
Before We even analyze that, can you just randomize yourselves again?
Any human algorithm is fine.
中文字幕
Let's try one other approach, because this feels kind of non-obvious, right?
I was fixing things, but I had to keep fixing things again and again.
中文字幕
Let me try to take a bigger bite out of the problem
this time by just selecting the smallest person.
中文字幕
OK, so your name again is?
[? JUHE: ?] [? Juhe. ?]
中文字幕
[? Juhe, ?] number 2-- that's a pretty small number,
so I'm going to remember that in sort of a mental variable.
中文字幕
4?
No, you're too big.
中文字幕
Too big.
Oh, what was your name again?
中文字幕
JAMES: James.
James.
中文字幕
James is a 1.
That's pretty nice.
中文字幕
Let me keep checking.
OK, James, in my mental variable is the smallest number.
中文字幕
I know I want him at the beginning.
So if you wouldn't mind coming with me.
中文字幕
And I'm sorry, we don't have room for you anymore.
If you could just-- oh, you know what?
中文字幕
Could you all just shuffle down?
Well, hm, I don't know if I like that.
中文字幕
That's a lot of work, right?
Moving all these values, let's not do that.
中文字幕
Let's not do that.
Number 2, could you mind just going where--
中文字幕
where--
JAMES: It's James.
中文字幕
--James was?
OK, so I've kind of made the problem a little worse in that,
中文字幕
now, number 2 is farther away from the goal.
But I could have gotten lucky, and maybe she was number 7 or 8.
中文字幕
And so let me just claim that, on average, just evicting the person
is going to kind of be a wash and average out.
中文字幕
But now James is in the right place.
Done.
中文字幕
Now I have a problem that's of size 7.
So let me select the next smallest person.
中文字幕
4 is the next smallest, not 8, not 5, not 7-- ooh, 2.
Not 3, 6.
中文字幕
OK, so you're back in the game.
All right, come on back.
中文字幕
And can we evict number 4?
And on this algorithm, if you will, I just
中文字幕
interpretively select the smallest person.
I'm not comparing everyone in quite the same way and swapping them pairwise,
中文字幕
I'm doing some of more macroscopic swaps.
So now I'm going to look for the next smallest, which is 3.
中文字幕
If you wouldn't mind popping around here?
[? Cahmy, ?] we have to, unfortunately, evict you,
中文字幕
but that works out to our favor.
Let me look for the next smallest, which is 4.
中文字幕
OK, you're back in.
Come on down.
中文字幕
Swap with 5.
OK, now I'm looking for 5.
中文字幕
Hey, 5, there you are.
OK.
中文字幕
So go here.
OK, looking for 6.
中文字幕
Oh, 6, a little bit of a shuffle.
OK.
中文字幕
And now looking for 7.
Oh, 7, if you could go here.
中文字幕
But notice, I'm not going back.
And this is what's important.
中文字幕
Like my steps are getting shorter and shorter.
My remaining steps are getting shorter and shorter.
中文字幕
And now we've actually sorted all of these humans.
So two fundamentally different ways, but they're both comparative in nature,
中文字幕
because I'm comparing these characters again,
and again, and again, and swapping them if they're out of order.
中文字幕
Or at a higher level, going through and swapping them again,
and again, and again.
中文字幕
But how many steps am I taking each time?
Even though I was doing fewer and fewer and I wasn't doubling back,
中文字幕
the first time, I was doing like n minus 1 comparisons.
And then I went back here.
中文字幕
And in the first algorithm, I kind of stopped going as far.
In the second algorithm, I just didn't go back as far.
中文字幕
So it was just kind of a different way of thinking of the problem.
But then I did what?
中文字幕
Like seven comparisons?
Then six, then five, then four, then three, then two, then one.
中文字幕
It's getting smaller, but how many comparisons is that total?
I've got like n people, n being a number.
中文字幕
Is not as bad as factorial.
We'd be here all day long.
中文字幕
But it is big.
It is big.
中文字幕
Let's go-- a round of applause, if we could, for our volunteers.
You can keep the shirts, if you'd like, as a souvenir.
中文字幕
Thank you, very much.
Let me see if we can't just kind of quantify that-- thank you, so much--
中文字幕
and see how we actually got to that point.
If I go ahead and pull up not our lockers, but our answers here,
中文字幕
let me propose that what we just did was essentially two algorithms.
One has the name bubble.
中文字幕
And I was kind of deliberately kind of shoehorning the word in there.
Bubble sort is just that comparative sort, pair by pair,
中文字幕
fixing tiny little mistakes.
But we needed to do it again, and again, and again.
中文字幕
So those steps kind of add up, but we can express them as pseudocode.
So in pseudocode-- and you can write this any number of ways--
中文字幕
I might just do the following.
Just keep doing the following, until there's no remaining swaps--
中文字幕
from i from 0 to n -2, which is just n is the total number of humans.
n -2 is go up from that person to this person,
中文字幕
because I want to compare him or her against the person next to them.
So I don't want to accidentally do this.
中文字幕
That's why it's n -2 at the end here.
Then I want to go ahead and, if the ith and the ith +1 elements are out
中文字幕
of order, swap them.
So that's why I was asking our human volunteers to exchange places.
中文字幕
And then just keep doing that, until there's no one left to swap.
And by definition, everyone is in order.
中文字幕
Meanwhile, the second algorithm has the conventional name of selection sort.
Selection sort is literally just that, where you actually
中文字幕
select the smallest person, or number of interest to you, intuitively,
again and again.
中文字幕
And the number keeps getting bigger, but you
start ignoring the people who you've already put into place.
中文字幕
So the problem, similarly, is getting smaller and smaller.
Just like in bubble sort, it was getting more and more sorted.
中文字幕
The pseudocode for selection sort might look like this.
For i from 0 to n -1, so that's 0 in an array.
中文字幕
And this is n -1.
Just keep looking for the smallest element between those two chairs,
中文字幕
and then pull that person out.
And then just evict whoever's there-- swap them,
中文字幕
but not necessarily adjacently, just as far away as is necessary.
And in this way, I keep turning my back on more and more people
中文字幕
because they are then in place.
So two different framings of the problem,
中文字幕
but it turns out they're actually both the same number of steps, give or take.
It turns out they're roughly the same number of steps,
中文字幕
even though it's a different way of thinking about it.
Because if I think about bubble sort, the first iteration, for instance,
中文字幕
what just-- actually, well, let's consider selection sort even.
In selection sort, how many comparisons did I have to do?
中文字幕
Well, once I found my smallest element, I
had to compare them against everyone else.
中文字幕
So that's n -1 comparisons the first time.
So n -1 on the board.
中文字幕
Then I can ignore them, because they're behind me now.
So now I have how many comparisons left out of n people?
中文字幕
n -2, because I subtracted one.
Then again, n -3, then n -4, all the way down to just one person remaining.
中文字幕
So I'll express that sort of generally, mathematically, like this.
So n -1 plus n -2 plus whatever plus one final comparison, whatever that is.
中文字幕
It turns out that if you actually read the back of the math
book or your physics textbooks where they have those little cheat
中文字幕
sheets as to what these recurrences are, turns out that n -1 plus n -2 plus n -3
and so forth can be expressed more succinctly
中文字幕
as literally just n times n -1 divided by 2.
And if you don't recall that, that's OK.
中文字幕
I always look these things up as well.
But that's true-- fact.
中文字幕
So what does that equal out to?
Well, it's like n squared minus n, if you just multiply it out.
中文字幕
And then if you divide the two, then it's
n squared divided by 2 minus n over 2.
中文字幕
So that's the total number of steps.
And I could actually plug this in.
中文字幕
We could plug in 8, do the math, and get the total number of comparisons
that I was verbally kind of rattling off.
中文字幕
So is that a big deal?
Hm, it feels like it's on the order of n squared.
中文字幕
And indeed, a computer scientist, when assessing
the efficiency of an algorithm, tends not to care too much
中文字幕
about the precise values.
All we're going to care about it's the biggest term.
中文字幕
What's the value in the formula that you come up
with that just dominates the other terms, so to speak,
中文字幕
that has the biggest effect, especially as n is getting larger and larger?
Now, why is this?
中文字幕
Well, let's just do sort of proof by example, if you will.
If this is the expression, technically, but I
中文字幕
claim that, ugh, it's close enough to say
on the order of, big O of n squared, so to speak, let's use an example.
中文字幕
If there's a million people on stage, and not just eight,
that math works out to be like a million squared
中文字幕
divided by 2 steps minus a million divided by 2, total.
So what does that actually work out to be?
中文字幕
Well, that's 500 billion minus 500,000.
And what does that work out to be?
中文字幕
Well, that's 499 billion, 999 million, 500,000.
That feels pretty darn close to like n squared.
中文字幕
I mean, that's a drop in the bucket to subtract 500,000 from 500 billion.
So you know what?
中文字幕
Eh, it's on the order of n squared.
It's not precise, but it's in that general order of magnitude,
中文字幕
so to speak.
And so this symbol, this capital 0, is literally a symbol
中文字幕
used in computer science and in programming
to just kind of describe with a wave of the hand,
中文字幕
but some good intuition and algorithm, how fast or slow your algorithm is.
And it turns out there's different ways to evaluate algorithms
中文字幕
with just different similar formulas.
n squared happens to be how much time both bubble sort and selection
中文字幕
sort take.
If I literally count up all of the work we
中文字幕
were doing on stage with our volunteers, it
would be roughly n squared, 8 squared, or 64 steps, give or take,
中文字幕
for all of those humans.
And that would be notably off.
中文字幕
There's a good amount of rounding error there.
But if we had a million volunteers on stage,
中文字幕
then the rounding error would be pretty negligible.
But we've actually seen some of these other orders of magnitude,
中文字幕
so to speak, before.
For instance, when we counted someone, or we searched for Mike Smith one page
中文字幕
at a time, we called that a linear algorithm.
And that was big O of n.
中文字幕
So it's on the order of n steps.
It's 1,000.
中文字幕
Maybe it's 999.
Whatever.
中文字幕
It's on the order of n steps.
The [? twosies ?] approach was twice as fast, recall-- two pages at a time.
中文字幕
But you know what?
That's still linear, right?
中文字幕
Like two pages at a time?
Let me just wait till next year when my CPU is twice
中文字幕
as fast, because Intel and companies keep speeding up computers.
The algorithm is fundamentally the same.
中文字幕
And indeed, if you think back to the picture we drew,
the shapes of those curves were indeed the same.
中文字幕
That first algorithm, finding Mike one page at a time looked like this.
Second algorithm finding him looked like this.
中文字幕
Only the third algorithm, the divide and conquer, splitting the phone book
was a fundamentally different shape.
中文字幕
And so even though we didn't use this fancy phrasing a couple of weeks
ago, these first algorithms, one page at a time, two pages at a time, eh,
中文字幕
they're on the order of n.
Technically, yes, n versus n divided by 2,
中文字幕
but we only care about the dominating factor, the variable n.
We can throw away everything in the denominator,
中文字幕
and we can throw away everything that's smaller than the biggest term, which
in this case is just n.
中文字幕
And I alluded to this two weeks ago--
logarithmic.
中文字幕
Well, it turns out that any time you divide something again, and again,
and again, you're leveraging a logarithmic type function,
中文字幕
log base 2 technically.
But on the order of log base n is a common one as well.
中文字幕
The beautiful algorithms are these--
literally, one step, or technically constant number of steps.
中文字幕
For instance, like what's an algorithm that might be constant time?
Open phone book.
中文字幕
OK, one step.
Doesn't really matter how many pages there are,
中文字幕
I'm just going to open the phone book.
And that doesn't vary by number of pages.
中文字幕
That might be a constant time algorithm, for instance.
So those are the lowest you can go.
中文字幕
And then there's somewhere even in between here
that we might aspire to with certain other algorithms.
中文字幕
So in fact, let's just see if-- just a moment--
let's just see if we can do this a little more succinctly.
中文字幕
Let's go ahead and use arrays in just one final way, using merge sorts.
So it turns out, using an array, we can actually
中文字幕
do something pretty powerfully, so long as we allow ourselves
a couple of arrays.
中文字幕
So again, when we just add sorting with bubble sort and selection sort,
we had just one array.
中文字幕
We had eight chairs for our eight people.
But if I actually allowed myself like 16 chairs, or even more,
中文字幕
and I allowed these folks to move a bit more,
I could actually do even better than that using arrays.
中文字幕
So here's some random numbers that we'll just do visually, without any humans.
And they're in an array, back, to back, to back, to back.
中文字幕
But if I allow myself a second array, I'm
going to be able to shuffle these things around and not just compare them,
中文字幕
because it was those comparisons and all of my footsteps in front of them
that really started to take a lot of time.
中文字幕
So here's my array.
You know what?
中文字幕
Just like the phone book-- that phone book example got us pretty far
in the first week--
中文字幕
let me do half of the problem at a time and then kind of combine my answer.
So here's an array--
中文字幕
4, 2, 7, 5, 6, 8, 3, 1-- randomly sorted.
Let me go ahead and sort just half of this,
中文字幕
just like I searched for Mike initially in just half of the phone book.
So 4, 2, 7, 5-- not sorted.
中文字幕
But you know what?
This feels like too big of a problem, still.
中文字幕
Let me sort just the left half of the left half.
OK, now it's a smaller problem.
中文字幕
You know what?
4 and 2, still out of order.
中文字幕
Let me just divide this list of two into two tiny arrays, each of size 1.
So here's a mini-array of size 1, and then another one of like size
中文字幕
7, but they're back to back, so whatever.
But this array of size 1, is it sorted?
中文字幕
No.
I'm sorry?
中文字幕
No.
No?
中文字幕
If this array has just one element and that element is 4--
There's only one thing you can do.
中文字幕
Yes, then it is sorted, by definition.
All right, so done.
中文字幕
Making some progress.
Now, let me kind of mentally rewind.
中文字幕
Let me sort the right half of that array.
So now I have another array of size 1.
中文字幕
Is this array sorted?
Yeah, kind of stupidly.
中文字幕
We don't really seem to be doing anything.
We're just making claims.
中文字幕
But yes, this is sorted.
But now, this was the original half.
中文字幕
And this half is sorted.
This half is sorted.
中文字幕
What if I now just kind of merge these sorted halves?
I've got two lists of size 1--
中文字幕
4 and 2.
And now if I have extra storage space, if I had like extra benches,
中文字幕
I could do this a little better.
don't I go ahead and merge these two as follows?
中文字幕
2 will go there.
4 will go there.
中文字幕
So now I've taken two sorted lists and made one bigger, more sorted list
by just merging them together, leveraging some additional space.
中文字幕
Now, let me mentally rewind.
How did I get to 4 and 2?
中文字幕
Well, I started with the left half, then the left half of the left half.
Let me now do the right half of the left half, if you will.
中文字幕
All right, let me divide this again.
7, list of size 1, is it sorted?
中文字幕
Yes, trivially.
5, is it sorted?
中文字幕
Yes.
7 and 5, let's go ahead and merge them together.
中文字幕
5 is, of course, going to go here.
7, of course, is going to go here.
中文字幕
OK.
Now where do we go?
中文字幕
We originally sorted the left half.
Let's go sort the right-- oh, right.
中文字幕
Sorry.
Now, we have the left half.
中文字幕
And the right half of the left half are sorted.
Let's go ahead and merge these.
中文字幕
We have two lists now of size 2--
2, 4 and 5, 7, both of which are sorted.
中文字幕
If I now merge 2, 4 and 5, 7, which element should come first
in the new longer list, obviously?
中文字幕
2.
And then 4, then 5, and then 7.
中文字幕
That wasn't much of anything.
But OK, we're just using a little more space in our array.
中文字幕
Now what comes next?
Now, let's do the right half.
中文字幕
Again, we started by taking the whole problem, doing the left half,
the left half of the left half, the left half of the left half of the left half.
中文字幕
And now we're going back in time, if you will.
So let's divide this into two halves, now the left half into two
中文字幕
halves still.
6 is sorted.
中文字幕
8 is sorted.
Now I have to merge them--
中文字幕
6, 8.
What comes next?
中文字幕
Right half-- 3 and 1.
Well, left half is sorted, right half is sorted--
中文字幕
1 and 3.
All right, now how do I merge these?
中文字幕
6, 8, 1, 3, which element should obviously come first?
1, then 3, then 6, then 8.
中文字幕
And then lastly, I have two lists of size four.
Let me give myself a little more space, one more array.
中文字幕
Now let me go ahead and put 1, and 2, and 3, and 4, and 5,
and 6, and 7, and 8.
中文字幕
What just happened?
Because it actually happened a lot faster, even though we were doing this
中文字幕
all verbally.
Well notice, how many times did each number change locations?
中文字幕
Literally three, right?
Like one, two, three, right?
中文字幕
It moved from the original array, to the secondary array, to the tertiary array,
to the fourth array, whatever that's called.
中文字幕
And then it was ultimately in place.
So each number had to move one, two, three spots.
中文字幕
And then how many numbers are there?
Well, they were already in the original array.
中文字幕
So how many times do they have to move?
Just one, two, three.
中文字幕
So how many total numbers are there, just to be clear?
There's eight.
中文字幕
So 8 times 3.
So let's generalize this.
中文字幕
If there's n numbers, and each time we moved
the numbers we did like half of them, than half, then half, well,
中文字幕
how many times can you divide 8 by 2?
8 goes to 4.
中文字幕
4 goes to 2.
2 goes to 1.
中文字幕
And that's why we bottomed out at one element, lists of size 1.
So it turns out whenever you divide something by half, by half, by half,
中文字幕
what is that function or formula?
Not power, that's bad.
中文字幕
That's the other direction.
It's a logarithm.
中文字幕
So again, logarithm is just a mathematical description
for any function that you keep dividing something again, and again, and again.
中文字幕
In half, in half, in half, in third, in third, in third, whatever it is,
it just means division by the same proportional amounts again,
中文字幕
and again, and again.
And so if we move the numbers three times, or more generally log
中文字幕
of n times, which again just means you divided n things again,
and again, and again, you just call that log n.
中文字幕
And there's n numbers, so n numbers moved
log n times, the total arithmetic here in question
中文字幕
is one of those other values on our little cheat sheet, which
looked like this.
中文字幕
In our other cheat sheet, recall that we had formulas that looked like this,
not just n squared and n, and log n, and 1, we have this one in the middle--
中文字幕
n times log n.
So again, we're kind of jumping around here.
中文字幕
But again, each number moves log n places.
There's n total numbers.
中文字幕
So n times log n is just, by definition, n log n.
But why is this sorted this way?
中文字幕
Well log n, recall from week 0 with the phone book example,
the green curve is definitely smaller than n. n was the straight lines,
中文字幕
log n was the green curved one.
So this indeed belongs in between, because this is n times n.
中文字幕
This is n.
This is n times something smaller than n.
中文字幕
So what's the actual implication?
Well, if we were to run these algorithms side by side
中文字幕
and actually compare them with something like this--
let me go ahead and compare these algorithms using this demo here--
中文字幕
if I go ahead and hit play, we'll see that the bars in this chart
are actually horizontal.
中文字幕
And the small bars represent small numbers,
large bars represent long numbers.
中文字幕
And then each of these is going to run a different algorithm-- selection
sort on the left, bubble sort in the middle,
中文字幕
merge sort, as we'll now call it, on the right.
And here's how long each of them take to sort those values.
中文字幕
Bubble's still going.
Selection's still going.
中文字幕
And so that's the appreciable difference, albeit with a small demo,
between n squared and something like log n.
中文字幕
And so what have we done here?
We've really, really, really got into the weeds of what arrays can actually
中文字幕
do for us and what the relationships are with strings, because all of it
kind of reduces to just things being back, to back, to back, to back.
中文字幕
But now that we kind of come back, and we'll
continue along this trajectory next time to be
中文字幕
able to talk at a much higher level about what's actually going on.
And we can now take this even further, by applying
中文字幕
other sort of forms of media to these same kinds of questions.
And we'll conclude it's about 60 seconds long.
中文字幕
These bars are vertical, instead of horizontal.
And what you'll see here is a visualization
中文字幕
of various sorting algorithms, among them selection sort, bubble
sort, and merge sort, and a whole assortment of others, each of which
中文字幕
has even a different sound to it because of the speed
and the pattern by which it actually operates.
中文字幕
So let's take a quick look.
[VIDEO PLAYBACK]
中文字幕
[MUSIC PLAYING]
This is bubble sort.
中文字幕
And you can see how the larger elements are indeed bubbling up to the top.
And you can kind of hear the ?] periodicity,
中文字幕
or the cycle that it's going in.
And there's less, and less, and less, and less work to do, until almost--
中文字幕
This is selection sort now.
So it starts off random, but we keep selecting the smallest human
中文字幕
or, in this case, the shortest bar.
And you'll see here the bars correlate with frequency, clearly.
中文字幕
So it's getting higher and higher and taller and taller.
This is merge sort now which, recall, does things in halves,
中文字幕
and then halves of halves, and then merges those halves.
So we just did all the left work, almost all the right work.
中文字幕
That one's very gratifying.
This is something called [? nom ?] sort, which is improving things.
中文字幕
Not quite perfectly, but it's always making forward progress,
and then kind of doubling back and cleaning things up.
中文字幕
Whew.
That was a lot.
中文字幕
Let's call it a day.
I'll stick around for one-on-one questions.
中文字幕
We'll see you next time.